<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The narrovv vvay, and the last iudgement deliuered in two sermons: the first at Pauls Crosse, the other elsewhere, by G.B. preacher of the word at Alphamston in Essex.</title>
            <author>Bury, George.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 162 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17332</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4179.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115853</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851070</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851070</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16325</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17332)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16325)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 869:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The narrovv vvay, and the last iudgement deliuered in two sermons: the first at Pauls Crosse, the other elsewhere, by G.B. preacher of the word at Alphamston in Essex.</title>
                  <author>Bury, George.</author>
                  <author>Brian, G., attributed name.</author>
                  <author>C. B., fl. 1607.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>88 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by R. Field] for Matthew Lownes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>G.B. = George Bury; sometimes attributed to G. Brian.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Edited by C.B.--STC.</note>
                  <note>"The last iudgement" has caption title.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 1029.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 1029 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; L4, final leaf, mutilated, with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16325:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16325:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE NARROW WAY, <hi>AND</hi> THE LAST IVDGEMENT, Deliuered in two Sermons: the firſt at Pauls Croſſe, the other elſewhere, by <hi>G. B.</hi> Preacher of the word at Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phamſton in Eſſex.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2. TIM. 2.7.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Conſider what I ſay, and the Lord giue thee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing in all things.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for MATTHEW LOWNES. 1607.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16325:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:16325:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL SIR VVILLIAM VVALGRAVE KNIGHT, OF BVERS IN ESSEX.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Worſhipfull, the generall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of your worthineſſe, your pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar affection to the Author (as I vnderſtand) and the knowne dignitie of this his worke, are the onely motiues of this my ſeeming boldneſſe in committing this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to the generall view, vnder your countenance and protection: which though I confeſſe I haue done without his leaue (as being modeſtly vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to encounter cenſure, or to oppoſe himſelfe an obiect to enuie) yet in that it hath receiued the currant ſtampe of approbation in the iudgement of the wiſeſt, and your ſelf (as I haue heard) an auricular iudge of the gracefull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuery; I haue in my ſelfe diſſolued doubt, and confidently thwart imputation with this aſſurance, that it cannot but be gratefull to the Reader, and come no leſſe acceptable to you. And though my ſelfe am vtterly vnknowne to you, yet as one bound to loue vertue euen in ſtrangers, I honour it in you, and haue bene ſo much the rather induced to this dedication, by how much (I am informed) you are truly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16325:3"/> affected to this my deare friend, and a cheriſher of his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuors. Sir, you cannot loſe by it; for learning will ſtill be prest to honour her <hi>Mecaenas,</hi> and ſuch as fauour Arts, chiefly thoſe that labor in Gods vineyard, &amp; (like lamps) conſume the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to giue light to others: I ſay ſuch good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and loue extended to religion and the profeſſors therof, is the treaſure layd vp in heauen, and ſhall remaine with the world of perpetuall record. Thus hauing done (as I thinke) a thankfull office, not greatly fearing the Authors diſpleaſure, if you but approue my act, I referre you to the enſuing matter: resting</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in deuotion, for your vertue-fauouring inclination, <hi>C. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:16325:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MATTH. 7.14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And few there be that find it.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the nature of euery man to affect long life here in this world; and this Almightie God knew well; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when he commaunded the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites, that they ſhould honour their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, as a prouocation to the performance of that du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, he propoſeth this reward vnto them,<note place="margin">Exod. 20.12.</note> that their dayes ſhould be long in the land which their Lord their God ſhould giue them. But albeit we are deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to liue long, and to ſee many dayes here in this life, yet becauſe reaſon and experience teacheth vs, that though we liue long, yet at one time or other we ſhall be diſſolued into our firſt duſt; for <hi>terraes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; in terram reuerteris,</hi> it was God his ſentence againſt all fleſh, <hi>Duſt thou art, and into dust thou ſhalt againe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne:</hi> therefore the deſire of mans nature ſtretcheth it ſelfe further, and not only content with long life here in this world, it affecteth a longer life, nay it affecteth an eternal life in the world to come. <hi>S. Pauls</hi> earneſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire was this, <hi>I deſire to be diſſolued, and to be with Chriſt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Philip. 1.23.</note> and old <hi>Symeon</hi> when he had once ſeene our Sauiour in the fleſh, he ſung this ſweete <hi>requiem</hi> to his owne ſoule, <hi>Lord, now let thy ſeruant depart in peace.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 2.29.</note> Albeit life were no doubt ſweete vnto theſe two Saints of God, yet their deſires aimed at a better thing; they were deſirous to change corruption for incorruption,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16325:4"/> mortalitie for immortalitie, a life temporall and full of ſorrowes, for a life eternall and full of comfort. Now as this was the deſire of theſe Saints of God, ſo no doubt it is (or at leaſt it ſhould be) the deſire of all the ſonnes of men: they ſhould not onely content themſelues with the preſent poſſeſſion of this life tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, but they ſhould hope &amp; looke for a life to come which is eternall. But in this it fareth with the world, as with thoſe old Iſraelites which came with <hi>Moſes</hi> out of Aegypt; for though they were for their number many thouſands, and all of them had a longing deſire to enter into the land of Canaan, yet it was only gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted but vnto two of them,<note place="margin">Numb. 14.30</note> vnto <hi>Caleb</hi> and vnto <hi>Ioſuah:</hi> ſo in the Aegypt of this world, in this place of palpable darkneſſe, though the deſires of moſt men be to enter into the kingdome of heauen, &amp; to raigne with Chriſt for euer; yet this heauenly bleſſing is not granted to all:<note place="margin">Math. 20.16.</note> for as Chriſt himſelfe ſaith, <hi>Many are called, but few are choſen;</hi> and as the way is broade, and the gate wide, that leadeth to deſtruction, in the verſe going before, that is, as the way of ſin, which leadeth men vnto hell, is eaſie, and many there be which enter in thereat: ſo in the beginning of this verſe, <hi>ſtraight is the gate, and narrow is the way that leadeth vnto life;</hi> that is, a holy and a religious conuerſation in this world, which is the high way to leade men to the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, is full of difficulties, and as our Sauiour addeth in the words which I haue read, <hi>they are but few that find it.</hi> To ſhew you how a holy and religious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation in this world, is that ſtraight gate and that narrow way that leadeth vnto life, wold be a diſcourſe both pleaſing and profitable; but becauſe that lies
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16325:4"/> without the bounds and limits of my text, and the drift of my text is onely this, that few men and few women doe find out this way of life; therefore the ſumme of my diſcourſe out of theſe words muſt be this, to examine thoſe lets and hinderances, why a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſo many as ſeeme to be in the way of a godly life, which is the way that leadeth to eternall life, ſo few there be that find it, that if we haue not found out this way of life, we may now ſeek after it, and find it; and if we haue already found it, that then we may perſeuere and continue in it. The lets then and the hinderances, why ſo few there are that do finde the way of life, are of two ſorts, <hi>ex parte quaerentis,</hi> and <hi>ex parte retrahentium,</hi> they either concerne our ſelues which are to ſeeke the way, or they are ſuch as do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure vs, and withdraw vs from the ſearch of it. Hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances in our ſelues that are to ſeeke the way, are eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially theſe three: the firſt is <hi>coecitas rationis,</hi> the blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our reaſon and vnderſtanding, which is not able of it ſelfe to diſcerne good from euill, the way of life from the way of death. The ſecond is <hi>peruerſitas voluntatis,</hi> the peeuiſhneſſe and peruerſneſſe of our wils, which, albeit we diſcerne the way, refuſeth to walke in it. And the third is <hi>defectus perſeuerantiae,</hi> a want of perſeuerance. For although in our reaſon and vnderſtanding we are able to diſcerne good fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euill, the way of life from the way of death, and in our will are moſt ready to apprehend it; yet for want of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance and continuance in ſo good a courſe, <hi>curri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus &amp; non comprehendimus,</hi> many of vs indeed do runne, but few of vs attaine our iourneys end. Of theſe three therfore in their order. And firſt for the blindnes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16325:5"/> of our reaſon, which being not able to diſcerne the way of life from the way of death, and by the fall of <hi>Adam</hi> preuailing ouer all the ſonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> is the firſt maine let in vs, why ſo few of vs do find out this way of life.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Blindneſſe of reaſon.</head>
               <p>The time was, when in man there were theſe three things; wiſedome of heart, puritie of life, ſtrength of bodie: but the ſoule of man by the ſuggeſtion of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, by the delectation which the apple promiſed, and by the conſent which man yeelded, fell from that high and beautifull Trinitie. His wiſdome was turned into blindneſſe of heart, his ſtrength was turned into weakneſſe of bodie, and the puritie of his life was changed into vncleane behauiour: ſo that concerning his ſtrength, that is now no better then a broken reed, as <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi> ſpake of Aegypt;<note place="margin">2. King. 18.21</note> and therefore <hi>Dauid</hi> moſt aduiſedly in the 28. Pſalme and 7. verſe, ſaid, <hi>Thou O Lord art my ſtrength.</hi> The puritie of his life, that,<note place="margin">Eſay 64.6.</note> ſaid <hi>Eſay,</hi> is like a ſtained and polluted cloth: and as for our reaſon and vnderſtanding, it is cleane de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed in <hi>Adam.</hi> All the knowledge and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of man, is either morall, naturall, or logicall, all which three in man by ſinne are periſhed. For the end of morall knowledge being this, to prefer good things before euill things, mans reaſon in this is ſo corrupted that the euill things of this world, which haue but an appearance of good, are preferred before good things indeed; and the good things indeed, they are reiected. You ſhall ſee this in the example of King <hi>Saul;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.30.</note> for to be honorable in the ſight of God, being true honour indeed, and to be honorable in the ſight of men,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16325:5"/> being <hi>bonum apparens,</hi> but an outward ſhadow or an appearance of true honour; the reaſon of King <hi>Saul</hi> there is ſo blinded, that he refuſeth to be honored in the ſight of God, and he deſireth the Prophet rather to honour him before the people. And whereas the end of our naturall knowledge, is to preferre thoſe things which are moſt profitable for the vſe of man; our reaſon for the moſt part is ſo blinded herein, that we preferre in our iudgements the things that are moſt hurtfull. And laſtly, whereas the end of our logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call or diſcourſing reaſon, is to diſcerne truth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, vanitie from lies; this likewiſe is ſo corrupted in vs, that we all, as the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſal. 4.2.</note> follow vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and ſeeke after leaſing: ſo that man hauing thus wonderfully loſt his reaſon wherein he was created, that which God ſpake in an Ironie concerning man, the very beaſts of the earth may ſay, and ſay truly,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.22.</note> 
                  <hi>Man is become like one of vs;</hi> and they haue their warrant for it out of the 49. Pſalme, and laſt verſe, <hi>Man being in honour, vnderſtood not, but is like the beaſts that periſh:</hi> nay in this he is farre worſe then the brute beaſts,<note place="margin">Eſay 1.3.</note> 
                  <hi>for the Oxe knowes his owner, and the Aſſe his maſters crib, but Iſrael hath not known, my people hath not vnderſtood.</hi> Mans reaſon without Gods grace, is euen as <hi>Sampſon</hi> without his guide when his eyes were out,<note place="margin">Iudg. 16.26.</note> without whoſe direction he could not finde the pillars of the houſe; nor can the natural &amp; carnal man find any pillar or principle of his faith, without Gods grace guiding his ſteps to it. <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith in the fourth of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> and tenth verſe, <hi>Vae ſoli, Wo be vnto him that is alone:</hi> and in this it is moſt true, for if mans reaſon be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Gods grace to guide it, wo be vnto it; it fals down,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16325:6"/> and there is none to helpe it vp: and therefore our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour makes a manifeſt diſtinction betweene theſe two, Gods grace, and mans reaſon, in that ſpeech of his to <hi>Peter:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 16.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed art thou Symon the ſonne of Ionas, for fleſh and bloud hath not reuealed this vnto thee, but my Father which is in heauen.</hi> It was not fleſh and bloud, it was not naturall and carnall reaſon, but Gods grace from aboue guiding his reaſon, that made <hi>Peter</hi> lay hold vpon Chriſt the way of life, and made Chriſt to pronounce him bleſſed. Therefore a little after, when as Gods grace and mans reaſon were ſeparated, and that <hi>Peter</hi> with carnall perſwaſions ſought to dehort Chriſt from his paſſion,<note place="margin">verſ. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Sir, pittie thy ſelfe, this ſhall not be vnto thee:</hi> Chriſt then biddeth him <hi>auant,</hi> not by the name of <hi>Peter,</hi> or the ſonne of <hi>Ionas,</hi> or <hi>Cephas,</hi> but of Sathan himſelf, <hi>Come behind me Sathan. Peters</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon was then alone, and the light of Gods grace had withdrawne her influence, and therefore no maruell if his counſell were ſuch, as was both againſt his owne and againſt the worlds ſaluation. The Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> was well acquainted with this blindneſſe of mans rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and therefore he doth vtterly reiect it as his guide in the way of life, and betakes himſelfe wholy to the guidance of Gods good ſpirit:<note place="margin">Pſal. 143.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Let thy good Spirit, O Lord, leade me into the way of righteouſneſſe:</hi> and Pſal. 27. <hi>Thou,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 27.1.</note> 
                  <hi>O Lord, art my light and my ſaluation:</hi> my light againſt ignorance, my ſaluation againſt impotencie: and in the 119. Pſalme, <hi>Giue me vnderstanding O Lord, and I ſhall keepe thy law.</hi> For as it was not poſſible for the Iſraelites to paſſe through the red ſea,<note place="margin">Exod. 14.</note> if God by a ſpeciall miracle had not prepared their way, and made a paſſage for them:<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. hom. <hi>40.</hi> in Math.</note> ſo for man to paſſe from the wayes
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16325:6"/> of death vnto the wayes of life, from the wayes of ſin to the wayes of righteouſnes, without the ſpeciall me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation and helpe of diuine grace it is not poſſible. This grace is that which is all in all vnto vs, and of this may that of our Sauiour be moſt truly verified,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn 15.5.</hi> Fulgent. de praed. ad Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xim. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out me, you can do nothing.</hi> This is <hi>praeueniens, cooperans, ſubſequens;</hi> it preuenteth vs, that when we are downe we may riſe vp, it accompanieth vs to vphold vs in our right courſe, and it muſt ſtil follow vs til we come to thoſe eternall beatitudes. For can we promiſe any more to our ſelues in finding out this way of life, then <hi>Dauid</hi> in the 119. Pſalme? <hi>I will runne O Lord</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the way of thy commaundements, when thou haſt ſet my heart at libertie.</hi> Can we runne with our feete, before our heart be prepared? or can we runne with our heart before God had enlarged it? Can we runne the way without the way, which is Chriſt Ieſus, a way which we cannot ſee, till our eyes be enlightened? not ſo: but when as God ſhall haue opened the eyes of our vnderſtanding, then with <hi>Dauid</hi> may we ſee the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull things of Gods law, and then with him may we runne the way of his commandements, when as God ſhall haue ſet our hearts at libertie. But before, we do all (euen the beſt of vs) lie lame, and impotent, like the cripple at the poole of Betheſda:<note place="margin">Iohn 5.5.</note> all the dayes and yeares of our times are ſpent like his without the caſe of our infirmities, and the vertue of the waters of life like thoſe waters in that poole, can neuer comfort vs. Seeing therefore that mans reaſon, ſince the fall of our firſt father <hi>Adam,</hi> is ſo cleane periſhed and decayed in it ſelfe, that of it ſelfe it is not able to make choiſe of that which is good, it remaineth for a truth, that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16325:7"/> Gods grace do accompanie mans reaſon, as the Angel did <hi>Toby,</hi> &amp; do go before it as the ſtarre did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the wiſe men vnto Chriſt; man ſhal neuer be able to walke in the way, nay he ſhall neuer be able to find out the way that ſhold leade him vnto life, but he ſhal go on like a naturall and carnall man in that broade beaten path which leadeth vnto death. So that you ſee mans reaſon, being not able to diſcerne good from euill, the way of life from the way of death, and by the fall of <hi>Adam</hi> preuailing ouer all the ſonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> to be one maine let in vs, why ſo few of vs do find out this way of life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>2. Peruerſneſſe of will.</head>
               <p>But let vs grant that mans reaſon were ſuch in him, and ſo well rectified, as that he could diſcerne good from euill, the way of life from the way of death; yet is there a ſecond let &amp; impediment in man, and that is <hi>peruerſitas voluntatis,</hi> the peeuiſhneſſe, the peruerſnes of his will. It was the error of the old Manichees, and it is at this day the practiſe of many prophane Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, euermore to caſt their ſinnes vpon God, excuſing themſelues, and accuſing him as the author of their iniquities; but the Scriptures are all directly againſt this; for as they make God to be the ſole cauſe and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of all happineſſe and good that befalleth man: ſo do they make man the ſole cauſe and author of all euil that betides himſelfe. It is Gods owne ſpeech in the Prophet,<note place="margin">Hoſea. 13.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Perditio tua ex teô Iſrael, ſalus ex me; O Iſrael thy ſaluation is from me, but thy deſtruction and ruine from thy ſelfe.</hi> As ſome locks there are, which will lock without a key, but without a key they neuer can be opened; ſo without a key, I meane without any other
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16325:7"/> meanes then their owne proper ſinnes, men may ſhut vp the the gates of Gods kingdome againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues; but without the key of Gods mercy and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous goodneſſe to them, it neuer can be opened. And as the Magitians of king <hi>Pharaoh</hi> had indeed power to bring plagues into the land of Aegypt,<note place="margin">Exod. 7.</note> but had no power to remoue the plagues thence: ſo men of them ſelues may be the authors of death vnto themſelues, but to giue vnto themſelues either the life of grace, or the life of glory, they haue no ability. God is ſo farre from barring vp the gate of his kingdom againſt any, that he ſetteth it wide open vnto all; <hi>I will not the death of a ſinner, but that he liue &amp; be ſaued;</hi> &amp; in the Goſpel, <hi>Come vnto me all yee that labor and are heauy laden,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 11.28.</note> 
                  <hi>and I will refreſh you;</hi> but ſuch is the peruerſeneſſe of mans will, ſuch the obſtinacy and rebellion of his corrupt nature, that though God doth offer grace, yet ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil not accept it, though he do as it were chalke him out the way that ſhould leade him vnto life, yet he will not walke in it, yea though he lay before him the crowne of eternall glory, as his reward and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, yet will he take no labour or paine for it. If then man by following the ſway of his crooked &amp; corrupt will, and by reiecting the good meanes which God giueth for his ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, do eternally periſh, let him not lay the fault vpon God, but vpon his owne peeuiſh &amp; peruerſe will. You ſhall ſee the truth of this by a moſt familiar example, and yet ſuch a one, as a whole gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councell hath thought fit for the illuſtration of it. If two men ſhould fall out of a ſhip,<note place="margin">Con Colonien.</note> and there were no way to ſaue them but by caſting forth a rope vnto them whereby they might be drawne vp; if one of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16325:8"/> them ſhall lay holde of it and be drawne vp, but the other in the peeuiſhnes and peruerſnes of his will ſhall refuſe the meanes of his deliuerance; is it not a cleare caſe that he which layes hold vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the rope, is ſaued by the great kindneſſe of him that threw it out, but the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which obſtinatly refuſeth it, periſheth by his own peruerſe will. Euen thus and no otherwiſe doth the caſe ſtand with vs; for by one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſin hath entred into the world, and we are all caſt out as it were from that arke of innocency in which we were created: But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the great mercy of God vnto man, he caſteth forth (if I may ſo ſpeake) a rope to ſaue vs, he hath ſent his ſonne into the world,<note place="margin">Iohn. 3.16.</note> 
                  <hi>That whoſoeuer beleeueth in him ſhould not periſh, but haue euerlaſting life.</hi> If then thou doſt lay hold vpon this meanes of thy ſaluation, by the hand of a liuely faith, thou muſt acknowledge God to be the author thereof; but if in the peruerſnes of thy will thou doſt refuſe it, then thy periſhing, it proceedeth from thy ſelfe, from thy obſtinate and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious will. This Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> knew to be moſt true, and therefore he was bold to ſay, <hi>Non eſt punitor Deus antequàm peccator homo: God neuer doth become a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſher, till man firſt becomes a ſinner,</hi> and we ſee it to be true in that ſpeech of <hi>Samuel</hi> vnto <hi>Saul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.26.</note> 
                  <hi>thou haſt wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully caſt away the Lord, and this</hi> (ſaith <hi>Samuel) is the cauſe of thy reiection, why the Lord hath caſt away thee.</hi> This peruerſnes of will was that, which in the daies of our Sauior kept the people of the Iewes from finding the way of life, and this is that which in theſe dayes of the Goſpel keepes many of vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> finding it. As <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaid vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Math. 23.37.</note> ſo may he not as truly ſay vnto vs, <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties volui ſed noluiſtis? How often wold I but you wold not?</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:16325:8"/> hath not God (to vſe that ſpeech in the Goſpel) piped vnto you by vs, and you haue not danced?<note place="margin">Luke. 7.32.</note> hath not he mourned vnto you by vs, and you haue not wept?<note place="margin">2. King. 4.31.</note> haue not we the Prophets, by the appointme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of our maiſter Chriſt, layed the ſtaffe of Gods iuſtice and Gods mercy vpon you that are dead in ſinne, as <hi>Gehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zi</hi> did his maiſters ſtaffe on the dead child, and like him you are not reuiued? hath not God called early and late vnto you (as vnto his people the Iewes) for an abſolute relinquiſhment of ſinne? hath he not cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (euen out of this place) by the ſhrilleſt trumpets that our land had, to magiſtrates, do iuſtly, to officers, liue not by bribes, to citizens, gaine not by vſury, to country gentlemen, grow not great by your poore neighbours oppreſſion, to all, do vnto others as you would be done vnto? Verily all this hath God done to bring vs to the wayes of life, but with very bad ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe; for ſo voluntary an oppoſition there is betweene mans peruerſe will, and this holy wil of God, that ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity hath the chaire ſtill, triuing writs are in moſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, Mammon is the cityzens God; and the morter, I may not ſay of al, but of many of your goodly buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings abroad, are tempered with the teares of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes. In this man reignes pride, in that man diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in a third enuy, in a fourth diſſimulation, in ſome bribery, in ſome periury, and in moſt hypocriſie; yea the whole land is couered with a flud of ſinne, as the old world with a flud of waters, and men ſwim vp and downe in it like fiſhes in the ſea, by the motion of their owne paſſions: ſo that that ſpeech which God taketh vp againſt the Iews, he may fitly take vp againſt vs, and ſay, I haue laboured to purge thy filthineſſe,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16325:9"/> but thou art not purged. God hath called to the carnal man to forſake his beaſtly pleaſures, to the couetous man to relinquiſh his inſatiable deſires, to the drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken man to forbeare barrelling vp Gods creatures in his belly, to the blaſphemers to leaue their ſwearing, to the hypocrites to leaue diſſembling, to all of vs to leaue ſinning, and to runne the way of his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements here in earth, that hereafter we might receiue a crowne of glorie in heauen: but what hath bin our anſwer? ſurely from the frowardneſſe of our hearts, and from the obſtinate rebellion of our peruerſe wils, we haue cried with <hi>Pharaoh, Quis eſt Dominus? Who is the Lord, that we ſhould ſerue him? or the God of</hi> Iacob, <hi>that we ſhould regard him?</hi> If therefore we are deſirous to haue this peruerſneſſe of our wil remoued from vs, which we know in moſt of vs to be a great meanes to keepe vs from the wayes of life, then our beſt courſe is euermore to ſubiect our wils vnto the will of God. Now the ſubiecting of our will vnto Gods will, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in theſe three:<note place="margin">Bernard. ſerm. contra peſſimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vitium ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudinis.</note> firſt that we abſolutely will thoſe things which we certainly know God willeth; then that we abſolutely nil thoſe things which we certainly know God nilleth: and laſtly, that in thoſe things whereof we are vncertaine whether God doth will or nill them, neither muſt we altogether will them, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther muſt we altogether refuſe them: &amp; ſo ſubiecting euery way our will vnto the will of God, this peruerſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of will, which in moſt of vs is a ſecond let to keep vs from finding the way of life, will be remoued.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Want of perſeuerance.</head>
               <p>Many there be which are willing and deſirous to attain eternal life, but yet they wil take no pains in the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16325:9"/> performance of Gods commandements, not vnlike vnto <hi>Naaman</hi> the Syrian, who comming to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet to be cured of his leaproſie, and the Prophet wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him onely to waſh in Iordan ſeuen times and he ſhould be cleane; he ſtomaketh the matter, and brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth out into theſe words,<note place="margin">2 King. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>I thought</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that he wold haue come out vnto me, and haue called on the name of his God, and haue layed his hands vpon me, and ſo I ſhould be healed.</hi> Here are three things which <hi>Naaman</hi> would haue done for him: firſt he will haue the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet to come forth: ſecondly, to call vpon his God: thirdly to lay his hands vpon him; but in the meane time there is not the leaſt paines mentioned to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken by himſelfe. And ſurely looke how it was with <hi>Naaman</hi> in the curing of his leaprous body; ſo it is with moſt of vs in the curing of our leaprous ſoules: we will haue God to do all for vs, but we will do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for our ſelues; our deſire ſhall be as great for the cleanſing of our leaprous ſoules, as <hi>Naamans</hi> was for the cleanſing of his leaprous bodie: but if it once come vnto this, thou muſt waſh thy ſelfe in Iordan ſeuen times, that is, thou muſt bathe thy ſinfull ſoule in the poole of repentance, and enter in at the ſtraight gate of a holy and religious life; then with <hi>Naaman</hi> we fall to murmuring, and we ſticke not to ſay in effect as he ſaid, that we looke for a more eaſie kind of cure in our conuerſion. But let vs grant that we are willing to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme whatſoeuer is preſcribed vnto vs for the finding of this way of life, yet vnleſſe we do perſeuere and continue euen vnto the end in that courſe, it is to ſmal purpoſe. To haue the Arke of God for a while,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 5.</note> did more endanger the Philiſtines then benefite them:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16325:10"/> and ſo for men to ſerue God for a while in a vertuous and religious courſe of life, will more hurt then helpe them;<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.21.</note> for better it is not to haue knowne the way of truth, then not to perſiſt in it; and farre more happie are thoſe men, who haue not entred at all into the wayes of life, then <hi>Iudas</hi> and ſuch wicked ones as he, whoſe ends are worſe then their beginnings. We do reade in the Goſpell,<note place="margin">Math. 20.8.</note> that ſome men came into the vineyard in the morning, and that ſome came in at noone, but none of theſe did receiue the reward but ſuch as ſtayed vntill night; to giue vs to vnderſtand, that they are not <hi>initia Chriſtianorum, ſed fines,</hi> not the good beginnings, but the good endings of Chriſtians which the Lord crowneth. The Church of Thyatira in the Reuelation, is much commended for this ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue:<note place="margin">Reuel. 2.19.</note> 
                  <hi>I know thy faith, and thy workes, and thy loue, and that thy laſt workes are more then thy firſt:</hi> and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of the Epiſtle vnto that Church, and of all the other Epiſtles is this; not he that drawes his ſword, not he that fighteth the battels of the Lord, not he that ſpends his bloud and after fainteth, but he that perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth and continueth to the end, ſhall eate of the tree of life.<note place="margin">Bern. Epiſt. <hi>129</hi>
                  </note> For without perſeuerance, <hi>nec qui pugnat victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam, nec palmam victor conſequitur;</hi> neither he which fighteth the Lords battels againſt ſinne and Sathan can haue the victory, nor he which ouercometh can haue the crowne of glorie. It is a notable remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance which our Sauiour Chriſt giueth vs in the Goſpell from the example of <hi>Lots</hi> wife,<note place="margin">Luke 17.31.</note> and which Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> amplifieth very fitly to this purpoſe, <hi>Memento vxoris Loth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>de Sodoma quidem eiectae, quia Deo credidit, ſed in via mutatae, quia retro aſpexit: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16325:10"/> Lots wife, how ſhe was brought indeed out of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, becauſe ſhe beleeued God, but was changed by the way into a pillar of ſalt, becauſe ſhe looked backe.</hi> God hath commaunded vs as he did <hi>Lot</hi> and his wife, that wee ſhould come out of Sodome, that is, that we ſhould forſake our ſinnes, and not ſo much as looke back vnto ſinne, but runne in haſt till we come into heauen which is our Zoar. If therefore with <hi>Lots</hi> wife we wil looke backe in our way to the pleaſantneſſe of ſinne, we ſhall be ſure with her to taſt the bitterneſſe of her puniſhment; for as ſhe, <hi>vbi reſpexit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 19.26.</note> 
                  <hi>ibi reman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit,</hi> where ſhe looked backe, there ſhe ſtood ſtill, and came not vnto Zoar where her life ſhould haue bene ſaued: ſo if once we haue abandoned ſinne, which is the broade way that leadeth vnto death, and haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into a holy and religious courſe, which is this nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row way that leadeth vnto life, if then with <hi>Lots</hi> wife we go not forward, but looke backward to our former delights of ſin, it is impoſſible for vs to come to Zoar, that is vnto heauen, where our ſoules and bodies ſhould be ſaued. They are our Sauiour Chriſt his own words, in the ninth of <hi>Luke</hi> and the laſt verſe, <hi>No man putting his hand vnto the plough and looking backe, is fit for the kingdome of God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 16.26.</note> The Iſraelites were comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, not once in a moneth, nor once in a weeke, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery day to gather Manna, except vpon the Sabboth day; to teach them and to teach vs, that till ſuch time as we come vnto that eternall Sabboth of our euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting reſt in heauen, we muſt neuer ſtand ſtill in the way of a godly life, but euery day be going forward. <hi>Apelles</hi> poſie was, <hi>Nulla dies ſine linea, Let no day paſſe from me without drawing one line at the leaſt:</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:16325:11"/> the Emperor was wont to ſay,<note place="margin">Sueton. in Tit. Amici, diem perdidimus. <hi>Ezech. 47.4.</hi>
                  </note> that he had loſt that day in which he did no good. As the waters in <hi>Ezechiel</hi> roſe by degrees, firſt to the ankles, then vnto the knees, then vnto the loines, and laſtly to the head; and as the wheate which Chriſt ſpeakes of,<note place="margin">Mark 4.28.</note> grew vp riper and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, firſt there was a blade, then the eare, then the full corne, and laſtly came the harueſt: ſo like thoſe waters we muſt grow higher and higher, till we come vnto our head Chriſt; and like that wheate we muſt grow riper and riper, til we come to the harueſt which is the end of the world. There is in Perſia a ſtone called <hi>Sele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plin. lib. vlt.</note> 
                  <hi>cuius interior candor cum Luna creſcit &amp; decreſcit,</hi> whoſe inward whiteneſſe increaſeth and decreaſeth as the Moone. The deuotion of Chriſtians muſt not be like this ſtone, ſtill changing, and continuing no longer in one moode then a ſparrow lights vpon the ground; but we muſt proceed in the way of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, euen as <hi>Abraham</hi> went to Canaan, that is, we muſt <hi>eundo pergere,</hi> ſtill be going; and as thoſe kine of the Philiſtines which bare the Arke of God,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 6.</note> though they were milch, &amp; had calues at home, yet without turning either to the right or left hand, they kept on their way to Bethſhemeſh: ſo hauing once ioyned ourſelues vnto the yoke of Chriſt, and bearing the arke of his law vpon our ſhoulders in the way of a vertuous life, though we haue many allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to draw vs backe, as thoſe kine had their calues; yet without turning either to the right or left hand, we muſt keepe our way to Bethſhemeſh, that is, vnto the houſe of the Sunne (for ſo the word ſignifieth) where the Son of God raigneth. In the 13. of Saint <hi>Matthew,</hi> the kingdome of God is deſcribed in this manner;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16325:11"/> 
                  <hi>It is as a grain of Muſterdſeed,</hi> at firſt the leaſt of al ſeeds;<note place="margin">Math. 13.31.</note> but when a man hath ſowne it in his field, it becometh firſt an herbe, then the greateſt of herbs, thirdly a tree, laſtly the birdes make arbours and ſhades in the bowes of it. Now why ſhould the kingdome of God be compared vnto this ſeede which is ſtill increaſing? ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily no better reaſon can be giuen for it then this, that we may all learne, not to ſtand ſtill in our Chriſtian growth, but to preſeuere and go on from grace vnto grace, till we become perfect men in Chriſt Ieſus. As the ſtar neuer ceaſed going,<note place="margin">Math. 2.9.</note> till it came vnto the houſe where Chriſt was: ſo if we be once entred into the way of a holy and religious life, we muſt neuer ſtand ſtill, but continue ſtill going, till we come vnto heauen where God is. If we haue faith, we muſt then go from faith to faith; if we haue loue, we muſt conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue and abide in loue; if we haue zeale, we muſt labor to be conſumed with zeale; if we giue almes, we muſt go a ſtep further, and giue it with chearfulneſſe; and as God hath continued a chaine of his good graces vnto vs, firſt by predeſtinating, ſecondly by calling,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.30.</note> thirdly by iuſtifying, fourthly by glorifying vs: ſo muſt we continue a chain of our graces towards God, by giuing al diligence,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.5.6.</note> as the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, to ioine vertue with our faith, and with our ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue knowledge, and with our knowledge te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perance, and with our temperance patience, and with our pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence godlineſſe, and neuer leaue ioyning the linkes of that golden chaine there ioyned, till our bodies and ſoules come to be diſioined. But (beloued) if the want of any vertue is to be lamented in this age, it is the want of this vertue of all vertues, perſeuerance. For
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16325:12"/> if we take a view of all eſtates of men, euen from the higheſt to the loweſt, ſhall we not be ſo far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> finding any increaſe or growth in Chriſtian duties, any going forward in the way of righteouſneſſe from grace vnto grace,<note place="margin">Indies deficit in agris agri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cola Cyp. con. Deme.</note> and from ſtrength vnto ſtrength, that we ſhall rather finde an vniuerſall falling away and defection in them? Is there not now (as S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> iuſtly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained in his time) a daily defectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the world, both of men, and of mens manners? Is there not a defection of the husbandman in the field, of the marriner at the ſea, of citizens in townes, of townſemen in villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges? Is there not a defection of innocency in the court, of iuſtice in iudgement, of concord in friendſhip, of workmanſhip in arts, of diſcipline in manners? Where is that zeale vnto the word, that hunger &amp; thirſt after the waters of the wel of life, that was wont to be amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs? Do we ſtill thirſt after theſe waters of the well of life,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 23.</note> as <hi>Dauid</hi> for the waters of the well of Bethlem? Nay rather are we not come vnto that fulneſſe and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tietie,<note place="margin">Numb. 11.7.</note> that we euen loath theſe waters of life, as Iſrael loathed Manna? If it were not ſo, then ſhould we not ſee ſo many in all places to loue better the threſholds of their doores, and their benches in aleboothes, then they loue the courts and ſeates of the Lords temple. The time was, when with gladneſſe we haue receiued this word vpon al occaſions, and entertained this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly food of our ſoules (as <hi>Elias</hi> foode for his body) with all thankfulneſſe,<note place="margin">1. King. 17.</note> euen then, when a blacke Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen hath brought it vnto vs, I meane men but mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly qualified. But now vnto ſo low an ebbe is our zeale and deuotion come, that though Angels from heauen bring it, I meane men excellently qualified, and able
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16325:12"/> ſufficiently to performe the worke of right faithfull Euangeliſts, yet men reiect it, nay which is worſe, they euen reſolue with <hi>Ahab</hi> not at all to heare <hi>Michea;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. King. 22.</note> not becauſe <hi>Michea</hi> propheſieth euill vnto them and not good,<note place="margin">2. Kin. 13.14.</note> but becauſe <hi>Michea</hi> is not a preacher qualified in all points according to their humours. But to leaue our loue vnto the word, let vs deſcend vnto our loue to thoſe that labor in the word, and for which loue many places in this land haue bene much commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. True it is, we haue bin as affectionate vnto them as king <hi>Ioas</hi> was to <hi>Elizeus,</hi> aſcribing more vnto them for the good of the whole land, then to al our chariots and our horſmen. It is true, we haue entertained them as the Galathians did Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> not onely as the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of God, but as Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe, yea we haue giuen no leſſe honour vnto them,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.13.</note> then the men of Lyſia vnto <hi>Barnabas</hi> &amp; <hi>Paul,</hi> freely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſing of theſe, as they confeſſed of them,<note place="margin">Act. 14.11.</note> that gods were come down vnto vs in the likeneſſe of men. I adde yet more, (that you may ſee vnto what a fearefull relapſe we are now in this age come,<note place="margin">Aquin. in hunc locum. l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note>) that double honor both of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and maintenance, (of countenance for their place, of maintenance for their ſeruice) which they that labour in the word are worthy of, ſaith S. <hi>Paul:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Timoth 5.17.</note> this double honour haue we yeelded and offered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them as their due in the ampleſt manner. But haue we ſo continued, haue we perſeuered in this loue? I muſt be faithful in my maiſters houſe with <hi>Moſes,</hi> and ſpeake a truth without flattery; I ſay boldly in the feare of God concerning this, as the Angell ſaith vnto the Church of Epheſus; we are become changelings,<note place="margin">Reuel. 2.4.</note> and haue loſt our former loue. For firſt for countenance;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16325:13"/> now euery vpſtart that hath ſcraped but a little pelfe together by the patchings of his braine, will be deadly oppoſite vnto no man more then to Gods miniſter. And as for maintenance, the time indeed was, when with the good Shunamite you haue prouided for <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias</hi> a chamber,<note place="margin">2. King 4.</note> a ſtoole, a table, and a candleſticke, and haue come vnto the Prophets, as Chriſt vnto the lame man at the poole of Betheſda,<note place="margin">Iohn 5.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Vis ſanus fieri?</hi> wilt thou be maintained? wilt thou be beneficed? But now ſo are the times, and with the times ſo are men changed, that you take from <hi>Elias</hi> his chamber, his ſtoole, his table, and his candleſtick. You do come vnto the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, not as Chriſt to the man before mentioned, <hi>Vis ſanus fieri?</hi> wilt thou be beneficed? but as <hi>Iudas</hi> to the high Prieſt, when he ſold his maſter, <hi>Quid mihi dabitis &amp; ego tradam vobis?</hi> what will you giue me and I will giue you a preſentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? And though the viſible iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God be vpon ſuch ſacriledge, for it thriues with them as the Arke of God among the Philiſtines,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 5.1.</note> and as the fleſh which an Eagle ſometime caried from an altar to her neſt; a coale of Gods wrathfull indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is caried with it, which in time conſumeth them and their yong: though I ſay, this viſible iudgement of God be vpon ſuch ſacriledge, yet the eies in our heads may faile with the expectation of that day, when the chambers of the Lord his houſe which <hi>Tobiah</hi> the Ammonite hath ſeized into his hands,<note place="margin">Nehem. 13.</note> ſhold be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againe to their ancient inſtitution for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Leuites. What ſhould I ſpeake in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular of that ſtedfaſtneſſe in faith, that modeſtie in words, that vprightneſſe in our actions, that mercie in our works, that diſcipline in our manners, that loue
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16325:13"/> and vnitie among neighbours and brethren, which in the Primitiue Church was the glory of the firſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and in ſome good meaſure hath heretofore bin ſeene among vs? Verily our coldneſſe in all theſe, as in the former, is a plaine demonſtration, that albeit we haue layed our hands vnto the plough of the beſt huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry in the whole world, yet we haue looked back; and albeit we haue made ſome ſmall entrance into the way of a vertuous life, yet we haue ſtarted aſide, and fallen from it again for want of perſeuerance. To draw this then to a concluſion. If we looke vpon all the ſons of <hi>Adam,</hi> who are bound by the commaundement of God to ſeeke after the way of life, and in them if we wel conſider, firſt the blindneſſe of their reaſon, which is not able of it ſelfe without Gods aſſiſting grace, to diſcerne the way of life from the way of death: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly the peruerſneſſe and obſtinacie of their wils, which albeit they know the way, yet refuſeth to walk in it: and laſtly their back-ſliding and want of perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, when haply they haue begun; if (I ſay) we conſider all theſe, bearing ſway for the moſt part with moſt of <hi>Adams</hi> ſonnes, we may then ſay, and ſay truly, euen as our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith in my text, <hi>They are few</hi> (yea very few) <hi>that do find the way of life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now as this is a manifeſt and certaine truth, that there be few that do find the way of life, if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the hinderances in our ſelues that ſeeke the way; ſo in the next place, if we ſhall take a view of thoſe things which do <hi>retrahere,</hi> which do allure vs and withdraw vs from the ſearch of this way, it will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare more plaine vnto vs. The things then which do vſually detaine and keepe vs backe from the ſearch of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16325:14"/> this way of life, are theſe three old and ancient ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of man,<note place="margin">Bern. medit. cap. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Mundus, Caro, Diabolus:</hi> the world, the fleſh, the diuell: and theſe three hauing drawne as many men vnto their part, as the Dragon drew the ſtarres of heauen with his taile, Reuelat. 12.4. it muſt needs follow that their number ſhould be very ſmall that go on in the way of life. I wil touch them all three in their order, and giue you ſuch caueats out of Gods booke againſt each of them, that if we be once entred into the way of a godly life, which is the narrow way that muſt leade vs to eternall life, neither the world with his inticeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, nor the fleſh with her allureme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, nor the diuell with his ſuggeſtions vnto ſinne, ſhall be able to withdraw vs from it. Firſt then for the world, which is the firſt enemy that oppoſeth vs in the way of life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The World.</head>
               <p>The tribes of <hi>Ruben</hi> and <hi>Gad</hi> being allured by the beauty and fatneſſe of the ground on this ſide Iordan,<note place="margin">Numb. 32.12.</note> thought the land of Canaan in goodneſſe to be farre inferiour to it, and therefore they did ſet vp their reſt there, and would go no further: and thus it is with moſt men, who are or ſhould be in this world trauel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers vnto the kingdome of heauen. For when they ſee the beautie and fatnes of this world wherin they liue, and that that is true of it which the citizens of Iericho ſaid once to <hi>Eliſha</hi> concerning their citie: Behold, the ſituation of the place is faire, and the ground pleaſant; therefore with thoſe two tribes of <hi>Gad</hi> and <hi>Ruben</hi> they wil go no further;<note place="margin">Math. 17.4.</note> but as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid in the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Chriſts glory, ſo ſay they beholding the glorie of this world, <hi>Bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt eſſe hîc,</hi> It is good for vs to be here.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:16325:14"/> And indeed as <hi>Vliſſes</hi> ſouldiers hauing once taſted of that poiſonous cup which the <hi>Lotor phagi</hi> gaue vnto them,<note place="margin">Hom. Odyſ. pag. <hi>247.</hi>
                  </note> they were neuer after deſirous to go into their owne country: ſo the greateſt part of men in the world being poiſoned as it were with the pleaſures and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights of it, they deſire to haue their reſidence ſtill in this life, &amp; they neuer looke after that way that ſhould bring them to eternal life. This the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> knew very well, and therefore to withdraw the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of men from the inticements of the world, he giueth this counſell, <hi>Loue not the world.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Epi. Ioh</hi> 2.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Vpon which words of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Serm. in verba Petri. Ecce nos reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quimus omnia</note> Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> maketh this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <hi>Vis noſſe quis ſit qui diligit mundum?</hi> Wilt thou know who it is that doth loue the world? then marke (ſaith he) what the Apoſtle addeth, <hi>Loue not the world nor the things of the world;</hi> as if he had ſaid, they that loue the things of the world, they are thoſe that loue the world, and in louing them, they are drawne from the wayes of life: for,<note place="margin">Auguſt. de ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis Dom. in Mat. ſerm. <hi>33.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>amor rerum terrenarum viſcus eſt ſpiritualium pennarum:</hi> The loue of earthly things is euen as birdlime to the ſpirituall wings of mens ſoules that they cannot mount to heauen. And as the ſpirit of God making <hi>Dauid</hi> apt and fit for the gouernment of the kingdome,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 16.</note> was not vpon <hi>Dauid</hi> till the ſame ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit was departed from <hi>Saul:</hi> ſo the ſpirituall bleſſings and graces of God cannot poſſibly reſt vpon men, till ſuch time as the loue of this world is departed from them. And therefore our Sauiour in the Goſpell very fitly anſwereth the man that was deſirous to follow him but to make a worldly gaine by that profeſſion, <hi>The foxes haue their holes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 9.58.</note> 
                  <hi>and the birds of the aire their neſts, but the Son of man hath not where to reſt his head:</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:16325:15"/> meaning that worldly affections and deſires had taken vp the poſſeſſion of his heart, and that therefore there was no roome in his heart for the ſon of man to lodge in. Now if you would know of me what the things of the world are which vſually withdraw moſt of vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wayes of life, becauſe to ſpeake thus of the world is too generall,<note place="margin">1. Ep. Ioh. 2.16</note> I anſwer from the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Iohn;</hi> they are ambition and pride of the world, luſt and concupiſcence of the fleſh, couetouſneſſe and inſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiable deſire of filthy lucre; theſe 3. Ambition, Luſt, &amp; Couetouſneſſe, which are not of the Father but of the world; theſe are the chiefe things of the world, &amp; vnto which al other worldly things may be referred, which withdraw vs from the way of life. You ſhal ſee the truth of all theſe together in one chapter, <hi>Luke</hi> 14. Where when a certain man had made a great ſupper, and bad many, (vnder whom is ſhadowed out God the Father inuiting men vnto the banquet of grace in this life, and ſo conſequently vnto that eternall ſupper of glory in the world to come:) the firſt excuſed himſelfe thus, that he had bought a farme; in which, ſay the expoſitors, are taxed the ambitious men of this world, whoſe whole delight is to gather farmes and Lordſhips into their hands, to be accounted Kings on earth. The ſeconds excuſe is, that he had bought a yoke of oxen, in which are taxed the couetous men, whoſe whole time of life is ſpent and employed in nothing elſe but in bargaining to get money. And the third mans anſwer is, that he had maried a wife, and therefore he could not com; by which we ſee, that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall concupiſcence is a great hinderance vnto men in following the way of life. But of that by it ſelfe anone:
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:16325:15"/> I will now amplifie a little the other two in this firſt branch of the world. Firſt then for the ambitious af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectation of worldly honors.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Ambition.</head>
               <p>In that the diuell in the fourth of <hi>Matthew</hi> did ſeeke to perſwade our Sauiour Chriſt to fall downe and to worſhip him, by promiſing him the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of the world; it is a cleare demonſtration, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the wiſedome of the diuell, that honour and preferment is able to draw men out of the right way; for although this temptation did not preuaile with Chriſt who was both God and man, yet it hath, and doth, &amp; wil preuaile with men. Our mother <hi>Euah</hi> had honor and royalty enough, ſhe was lady of Paradiſe, and not onely of Paradiſe, but of all the earth beſides; and yet neither the earth nor Paradiſe can content her mind, but ſhe muſt either be <hi>Similis altiſsimo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>like vnto the moſt high,</hi> ſhe muſt be the Queene of heauen, or ſhe will breake the commandement of God. Did not this thinke you, worke ſtrongly vpon <hi>Balaam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Numb. 22.</note> when it made him ſaddle vp his aſſe, and in hope of high fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uors and preferments from the king, to ride poſt with the Princes of Moab to curſe Gods people? Hath not this cauſed <hi>Abimelek</hi> to become a butcher to his owne brethren? and <hi>Herod</hi> the king,<note place="margin">Iudg. 9.5. <hi>Ioſeph. lib.</hi> 15. <hi>Antiq. cap.</hi> 2.</note> that he might more pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceably inioy that crown into which before moſt am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitiouſly he had crept, not to regard the life, either of friends, of wife, of children?<note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.</note> Did not this cauſe <hi>Abſolon</hi> moſt vnnaturally to thirſt after the life and crowne of his owne father?<note place="margin">Heſt. 3.6.</note> and <hi>Haman</hi> to thirſt after the life not of one priuate man alone, but of all the people of the Iewes in the kingdome of <hi>Aſſuerus?</hi> The trap which
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:16325:16"/> the diuell ſet to inſnare our mother <hi>Eue,</hi> was hope of higher dignity,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.5.</note> and this one ſubtlety of his, <hi>Eritis tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam Dij, You ſhall be as Gods ſhining in honor and glory aboue other men,</hi> it hath heretofore bene, and it is at this day, the foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; root of rebellions, treaſons, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, thefts, &amp; of ſuch damnable machiauellia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> policies as are hardly to be found euen among the Gentiles; &amp; as it was the ſpeech of <hi>Agrippina</hi> the Emperour <hi>Neros</hi> mother, when ſhe heard that her ſonne <hi>Nero</hi> ſhould be Emperor,<note place="margin">Sueton. in Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rone.</note> but yet ſhould kill his mother in his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire; <hi>Occidat, modò imperet,</hi> Let him kill me, ſo he may be Emperour: ſo I pray God that by the perſwaſion of the diuell, it be not a ſetled reſolution in the hearts of many, Let me periſh, not temporally with <hi>Agrippi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> but eternally both in ſoule and body, if ſo be in this life I may haue places of preferment, either in church or common-wealth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Riches.</head>
               <p>Now for the wealth and riches of the world, that they likewiſe as well as worldly honours are a meanes to draw vs from the wayes of life, it is a caſe clearely decided by our Sauiour Chriſt in the 19. of Saint <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 19.20.21</note> for when the yong man had made this queſtion vnto Chriſt, <hi>Maiſter, what ſhall I do to attaine eternall life?</hi> and Chriſt his anſwer was, <hi>Keepe the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;</hi> and his reply to that was, <hi>I haue kept them from my youth vp;</hi> and Chriſt his replication to him againe was, <hi>Yet thou wanteſt one thing, Sell all that thou haſt, and giue it to the poore:</hi> at that ſaying (ſaith the text) he departed ſorowfull, and the cauſe of his ſorow is there noted to be this, <hi>He had great poſſeſsions and was rich:</hi> and therefore our Sauiour is bold in the 23. verſe to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:16325:16"/> ſet downe this as a concluſion, that a rich man ſhall hardly enter into the kingdome of heauen. But were it not a caſe thus cleared by our Sauiour Chriſt, yet if we will but looke into the qualities and conditions of rich men, we ſhall find their wealth to haue bene, and to be vnto them an occaſion of many grieuous and groſſe ſinnes, by meanes whereof they are kept from the wayes of life. For to begin firſt with the ſinne of pride (a ſinne ſo hatefull in Gods eyes, that it caſt our firſt parents out of Paradiſe, and <hi>Lucifer</hi> from heauen to hel,) to begin (I ſay) with the ſinne of pride, mark it when you wil, you ſhall ſee that where ſtore of wealth is, there commonly is ſtore of pride: and therefore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other charges which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> giues to <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> this is not left out,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.17.</note> namely that he ſhould charge rich men that they be not high minded. And the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then man <hi>Tully</hi> deſcribing the qualities of the rich,<note place="margin">In Orat. de lege Agrar ad Quirit.</note> which for the moſt part are very intollerable, among others he ſetteth downe pride for one, and his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance is in the men of Campania; <hi>Campani ſemper ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbi bonitate agrorum &amp; fructuum:</hi> The men of Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pania are euer high minded and proud, in regard of the ſtore of fruites, and of corne which their country yeeldeth: and it is not only true in them,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Lib. Rhet.</note> but as <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi> ſaith, it holdeth in all rich men in al countries what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer. But if this ſinne of pride did onely accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie our earthly riches, it were well; <hi>ſed ecce venit Gad,</hi> behold there are a great companie of ſinnes more: for as they do breed in vs pride of heart, to the contempt of our poore neighbours; ſo do they corrupt our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories to the forgetfulneſſe of God. This <hi>Moſes</hi> knew to be true, and therefore he giueth this caueat to the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:16325:17"/> children of Iſrael:<note place="margin">Deut. 6.10.</note> 
                  <hi>When the Lord thy God hath brought thee into the land which he ſware vnto thy fathers to giue thee, with goodly cities which thou buildedſt not, with houſes full of all manner of goods which thou filledſt not, with vineyards and Oliue trees which thou plantedſt not; when thou haſt eaten and art full, then take heed and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware that thou forget not the Lord thy God.</hi> Yea ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon a thing it is for worldly riches to make men for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get God, that <hi>Salomon</hi> himſelfe, though he were wiſer then other men, and ſo conſequently better able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt ſinne; yet he maketh it his earneſt ſute vnto God, <hi>O Lord giue me neither pouertie nor riches;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 30.8.</note> not pouerty, leſt I ſteale, and take the name of my God in vaine; &amp; not riches, leaſt I be too full and deny thee, and ſay, Who is the Lord? For albeit I perſwade my ſelfe, that there be many both in this citie and in other places of the land, who in a thankfull remembrance of Gods goodneſſe and bountie to them, do confeſſe with <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 32.10.</note> 
                  <hi>I came ouer this Iordan with my ſtaffe, and lo I haue now gotten two bands:</hi> I came poore and without pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion to this place, and lo I haue not onely gotten great wealth, but ſuch honour alſo, that I ſit with Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: yet looke we generally vpon the courſes of the rich, and we ſhall find it to be true, that as the Moone when ſhe is at the ful, ſhe is then fartheſt from the Sun, of whom ſhe doth receiue her light; ſo men, when they are fulleſt of earthly riches and bleſſings, they are then commonly fartheſt from God, from whoſe ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe they haue receiued them. And as pride and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfulneſſe of God do accompany our earthly riches; ſo a third euil of them is, that they make men to offend and ſin in luxury. In the twelfth of <hi>Luke</hi> and 19. verſe,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:16325:17"/> the great rich man, whoſe grounds brought foorth fruite plentifully, he thinkes on nothing but his belly; Soule, now thou haſt much goods for many yeares, liue at eaſe, eate, drinke, follow thy pleaſure. And in the fifteenth of <hi>Luke,</hi> the yonger of the two brethren hauing receiued that portion of goods which belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to him, he ſpends it all in few dayes in gluttonie, and venery. Fourthly, whereas the word of God is a ſpeciall meanes to bring vs to ſaluation, theſe worldly riches choke the word, and make it vnfruitfull. You may ſee it in the thirteenth of Saint <hi>Mathew,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 13.22.</note> where our Sauiour expounding the parable of the ſower, ſaith thus: <hi>He that receiues the ſeed among the thornes is he that heares the word, but the care of the world &amp; the deceitfulneſſe of riches choke the word in him, and he is made vnfruitful.</hi> Fiftly, whereas it is a true note of the true child of God, euermore to be weary of this ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful world,<note place="margin">Philip. 1.23.</note> and to deſire with Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to be diſſolued and to be with Chriſt; theſe earthly riches do make thoſe which haue them loth to die, yea with a good will a rich man would not ſo much as thinke of death: ſaith the wiſe man: <hi>O death,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 41.1.</note> 
                  <hi>how bitter is the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of thee to a man that liues at reſt and eaſe in his poſſeſsions?</hi> And as worldly riches are an occaſion of theſe euils; ſo laſtly are they the cauſe of Idolatry, yea the couetous affectation of them, ſaith Saint <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.5.</note> is Idolatry. And that it is ſo, the Diuines collect it thus: for whereas the true worſhip and ſeruice of God doth conſiſt in theſe three, <hi>in diligendo, honorando,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bonauen. Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiloq. part. <hi>1.</hi> ſect. <hi>22.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>&amp; in ipſo confidendo:</hi> In louing God, in honoring God, in put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our whole confidence and truſt in God. The Mammoniſts of this world do take all theſe from God
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:16325:18"/> and giue them to their riches. For firſt, though the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept runne thus,<note place="margin">Deut. 6.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt loue the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoule, and with al thy might,</hi> yet do theſe men take this loue from God, and beſtow it on their wealth: and therefore Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> that he might meet with this,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Epi Ioh.</hi> 2.15 Pſal. 62.2.</note> he giueth this caueat: <hi>Loue not the world;</hi> and the Prophet <hi>Dauid: If riches increaſe, yet</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>do not ſet your hearts vpon them.</hi> And for the ſecond which is honor, wheras it is the Angels ſpeech vnto vs that dwell vpon the face of the earth:<note place="margin">Reuel. 14.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Honor and worſhip him that hath made the heauen &amp; the earth, the ſea and the fountaines of waters;</hi> theſe men, as it is in the eight of <hi>Hoſea</hi> and fourth verſe, <hi>Of their ſiluer and their gold do they make them Idols,</hi> their ſiluer and gold is the god they worſhip. And laſtly for confidence and truſt,<note place="margin">Prou. 16.20.</note> whereas the wiſe man ſaith: <hi>Bleſſed is the man that truſteth in the Lord:</hi> theſe are like vnto the man of whom the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaketh:<note place="margin">Pſal. 52.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Behold the man that tooke not God for his ſtrength, but truſted in the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of his riches.</hi> So that the riches of the world, as wel as the honors of the world, are occaſions, you ſee, vnto men of many ſinnes, by which they are drawne from the wayes of life. If therefore we are deſirous to preuent theſe and the like inticements of the world, leaſt by them we be deceiued, and ſo cauſed to erre from the paths of life; our beſt courſe is euermore to conſider of this world as it is, and not as it ſeemeth. <hi>Caligula</hi> the Emperour ſet golden loaues and other ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices of whole gold before his gueſts, and bad them eate. Indeed they had a glorious ſhew to looke vpon, but there was nothing in them to eate and to drinke, for the contentation of nature. And ſuch, &amp; no other
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:16325:18"/> are the dainties which the world propoſeth vnto vs, both in wealth and honour; they haue (I confeſſe) a glorious ſhew to the eye, but the ſubſtance of them being well conſidered is but vanitie. Firſt for honor, let <hi>Haman</hi> ſpeake, who was next vnto the King,<note place="margin">Eſter 2.1.</note> and with him was alone inuited to the banquet of Queen <hi>Heſter;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſter 5.4.</note> and when he hath ſaid all that he can for his honor, yet the concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all muſt be this, that it was but vanitie: for in that day in which he was entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with ſuch royaltie at the banquet of Queene <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſter 7.1.10.</note> in that ſame day was he hung vpon the gallowes which he made for <hi>Mordecay;</hi> at the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the King, who before had highly honoured him at the requeſt of the Queene, who before had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uited him. How highly was our Sauiour graced and dignified by the people of the Iewes? In the 6.<note place="margin">Iohn 6.15.</note> of <hi>Iohn</hi> they would haue made him King; in the 12.<note place="margin">Iohn 12.13.</note> of <hi>Iohn</hi> they cut downe branches of palme trees, and meete him ſinging ſweetly, <hi>Hoſanna, Bleſſed art thou that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt in the name of the Lord:</hi> but ſee the inconſtancy of this people, and the mutabilitie of this worldly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; they who before had cried <hi>Hoſanna, Bleſſed art thou that comest in the name of the Lord,</hi> not many daies after, euen the fift day,<note place="margin">In cap. <hi>2.</hi> Mat.</note> as Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, they crie as earneſtly againſt him, <hi>Crucifige, let him be crucified.</hi> So true is that which Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> hath concerning worldly honour, <hi>Vanitas eſt huius ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi dignitas, cum magna expectatione ſperatur vt veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at, ſed non poteſt teneri cum venerit:</hi> The honours and preferments of the world are but meere vanities, they are long looked for of men to come with great expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation; but when once they haue them, they are ſo
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:16325:19"/> ſhort and fleeting, that they cannot keepe them. And for the wealth and riches of the world, if you will not beleeue <hi>Salomon</hi> vpon his word when he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them vanity,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.2.</note> yet beleeue them to be vanitie, euen for this, becauſe they will haue either thy end, or their end;<note place="margin">Iob 1.</note> their end, as they had in <hi>Iob,</hi> who from great wealth came vnto a low ebbe of pouerty: or thy end, as they had in the rich man, who when he ſung a long laſting <hi>requiem</hi> to his ſoule in the multitude of his ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,<note place="margin">Luk. 12.19.20</note> had his ſoule the ſame night taken away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him. And is there then (beloued) ſuch vanity in this world, &amp; in the beſt things which this world propoſeth both in wealth and honor; and ſhall we for the gaining of this, leaue the gaining of ſuch a world as is not ſubiect vnto vanitie? Shal we leaue gold for droſſe, pearle for glaſſe, heauen for earth, the permanent &amp; euerlaſting ioyes of the one, for the momentary and tranſitory delights of the other? The eyes of the brute beaſts are turned downward to the earth, to ſeeke for nothing but meate for their bellies; <hi>At os homini ſublime dedit;</hi> But the face and countenance of man is lifted vpward vnto heauen, to behold God who hath made all for man, and man for himſelfe: let vs then leaue the world and the things of the world vnto the beaſts, to whom properly it belongeth, and let vs ſend vp the affections of our hearts vnto heauen, where our inheritance is reſerued.<note place="margin">Gen. 28.11.</note> And as <hi>Iacob</hi> in that his iourny vnto Padan-Aram is ſaid to ſleepe in the way; ſo while we liue here in this world, which is nothing elſe but a paſſage to a better life, or if you will ſo call it, our way and iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to the heauenly Canaan, let vs ſleepe and be at reſt from the deſire of temporall things whatſoeuer:
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:16325:19"/> let heauen become our obiect, and earth become our abiect. The deſires of our hearts, let them be placed vpon things aboue: as for things beneath, let them be vnto vs as vnto Saint <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Philip. 3.8.</note> euen <hi>loſſe and dung in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the excellent knowledge of Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> as vnto <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: a ſhadow and a dreame, and lighter then theſe; as vnto <hi>Plato</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> nothing, and worth nothing. Let vs ſay with <hi>Peter</hi> and with <hi>Peters</hi> affection, <hi>Behold maſter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 19.27.</note> 
                  <hi>we forſake all and follow thee:</hi> let vs ſay with Saint <hi>Paule I am non ego, ſed viuit in me Chriſtus,</hi> Now it is not I,<note place="margin">Galat. 2.20.</note> but Chriſt which liueth in me; that is, as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds thoſe words very fitly to this purpoſe: <hi>Ad alia quidem omnia mortuus ſum, non ſentio, non attendo, non curo; ſiqua verò ſunt Chriſti, haec viuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inueniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; paratu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> Concerning theſe earthly and worldly matters, I haue no ſenſe or feeling of them, by my reaſon I condemne them, and from my heart I abandon them; but if there be mention made of Chriſt, and of finding the waies of life, then my decaied ſpirits gather ſtrength, then all the powers and faculties of my ſoule will me to cry with the Prophet <hi>Dauid: Paratum eſt cor meum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 57.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne:</hi> My heart is ready ô Lord, my heart is ready. For otherwiſe if cleauing, by an inordinate affection and loue, to this world and the things of it, we neglect and reiect the waies of life;<note place="margin">Deut. 3.27.</note> as <hi>Moſes</hi> from the top of Piſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gah might behold with his eyes the land of Canaan, but might not enter into it: &amp; as the Syrians did heare <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſpeake, whom they deſired to take,<note place="margin">2. King. 6.29.</note> but could not take him: ſo with the outward eares of our bodies we may heare of the ioyes of another life, and with the intellectuall eyes of our minds we may ſee that great
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:16325:20"/> glory which the iuſt ſhall haue heareafter, but our ſelues ſhall neuer come into heauen, our ſelues ſhall neuer be partakers of it. And as <hi>Lyſimachus</hi> king of Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia, hauing yeelded himſelf into the hands of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies for a cup of cold water to quench his thirſt, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out;<note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> 
                  <hi>O me hominem infoelicem, qui tantillae voluptatis gratia tantum amiſerim regnum,</hi> ô miſerable and wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched man that I am, who for ſo ſhort a pleaſure haue parted with ſo glorious a kingdome as the kingdome of Lydia: ſo when we ſhall ſee in the laſt day that by yeelding too much vnto this world, and the things of it, we haue parted with the wayes of life, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently haue yeelded vp our ſelues into the hands of our ſpirituall enemies, we ſhal mourne and lament, we ſhall ſigh and wring our hands; and all the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full torments which we ſhall then ſuffer, ſhall not wound and vexe vs ſo ſore, as this one conſideration, namely when we ſhall call to mind, that for the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary and tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſitorie pleaſures of this word, we haue parted with that ſame exceeding,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.17.</note> eternall, ſurpaſſing weight of glory in the kingdome of heauen. And thus much ſhall ſerue to haue ſpoken of the world, and of the things of the world, which is the firſt enemie that oppoſeth himſelf againſt man to keepe him from the way of life. I com to the ſecond enemy, and this is, <hi>Caro.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The carnall lusts and deſires of the fleſh.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th. lib. <hi>10.</hi> c. <hi>5</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> diſputing of the nature and efficacie of pleaſure, ſaith this, that a man which taketh greater de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in inſtrumentall then in vocal muſick, if he heare the ſame muſitian both to play vpon his inſtrument and to ſing; the pleaſure and delight which he concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:16325:20"/> in hearing of the inſtrument, doth ſo leade away his affections, that he hath no care at all of the voice: and as this is true in muſick, ſo is it true (ſaith he) in all other things, when we intend two things at once, that which breedeth the greater pleaſure and delight, for the moſt part doth euermore exclude the leſſe. There being then in man two kinds of affections, carnall and ſpirituall, and all men for the moſt part taking greater delight in their carnall, then in their ſpirituall affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; of neceſſitie it muſt come to paſſe, that their car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall affections do ſwallow vp their ſpirituall, and ſo conſequently they are ſo farre from finding the waies of life, that there is in them no deſire, no luſt at all vnto it. The ſect and companie of the Epicures (who main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained carnal pleaſure to be the onely <hi>ſummum bonum</hi> of this life) did ſwarme in greater abundance then any other ſect did: <hi>non quòd veri aliquid afferat,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lactan. de falſa ſap. cap. <hi>17.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſed quia multos populare nomen voluptatis inuitat;</hi> not becauſe (ſaith <hi>Lactantius</hi>) there was any truth at all in their doctrine, but becauſe the popular name of carnal plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is able to draw a world of men to it. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> confeſſeth of himſelfe,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.18.</note> that in his fleſh there dwelt no good thing, and that he ſaw a law in his members re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belling againſt the law of his mind; and not that only,<note place="margin">verſ. 23.</note> but that it led him away captiue to the law of ſinne, inſomuch that for very griefe of heart he breaketh out into theſe words: <hi>Miſer homo:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">verſ. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliuer me from the bodie of this death?</hi> Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> writeth of himſelfe,<note place="margin">In Epiſt. ad Euſtoch.</note> that albeit he led a moſt ſtrict and auſtere life in the wilderneſſe, exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing himſelfe continually in prayer, and bringing his body vnder by long and often abſtinence; yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:16325:21"/> that he was vehemently aſſaulted by the luſts and deſires of the fleſh, euen as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was. And ſurely, if the mortified fleſh of theſe Saints of God, mortified no doubt by prayer, and by long and often faſting, did notwithſtanding as themſelues con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, leade away their ſoules captiue to the law of ſinne; then may we well conclude, that the vntamed fleſh of vs vnbridled men, will forcibly and with vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence miſleade our ſoules from the way of life. Our Sauiour Chriſt ſpeaking of his owne paſſion, is ſo farre from the feare of death in himſelfe, that he ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth his diſciples againſt it, ſaying, that he would go to prepare a place for them;<note place="margin">Iohn 14.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> but afterwards when he was to die vnto the world, and to go to his father, then he ſeemes to be of another mind; then <hi>tranſeat à me Calix,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 22.42.</note> 
                  <hi>Father if it be thy will, let this cup paſſe from me.</hi> And what was the reaſon of this? ſurely that in the 26. of <hi>Mathew</hi> and 41. verſe, <hi>The ſpirit is ready, but the fleſh is weake.</hi> The ſpirit indeed of many men is prone vnto that which is good, they deſire ſo to runne the race of a godly life here, that hereafter they may receiue a crowne of glory; but ſo it is that mans life is as <hi>Iob</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth,<note place="margin">Iob 7.1. Gal. 5.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Militia ſuper terra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> a warfare vpon earth; the fleſh ſtill luſting againſt the ſpirit, and the ſpirit againſt the fleſh, and that which is moſt to be lamented, in moſt of vs the fleſh extinguiſheth the ſpirit. <hi>Sampſon</hi> was a ſtrong and valiant man,<note place="margin">Iudg. 14.6.</note> he encountred a Lion, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercame him, but encountring with the fury of his owne luſtful paſſions, he could not maſter them. <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes incendit alienas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iudg. 16.17.</hi> Ambroſ. in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pol. Dauid.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; vnius ipſe mulieris accenſus igni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo, meſſem ſuae virtutis amiſit:</hi> He ſet fire indeed on the harueſts of other men, but himſelf being inflamed
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:16325:21"/> with the fire of luſt, loſt the harueſt of all his vertues. <hi>Salomon</hi> built a goodly Temple vnto God, but in the meane time his owne bodie, which ſhould haue bene (as the Apoſtle ſaith of all our bodies) the temple of the holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.19.</note> was by luſt made the member of a harlot.<note place="margin">Gen. 3.6.</note> This is that <hi>Eue</hi> that perſwadeth <hi>Adam</hi> to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden fruites:<note place="margin">Gen. 39.7.</note> this is that Aegyptian <hi>Putipharis</hi> that eggeth on innocent <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to filthines:<note place="margin">Iudg. 4.18.</note> this is that <hi>Iahel</hi> that ſeduceth <hi>Siſera</hi> with fained affection: this is that <hi>Dalilah</hi> which lulleth <hi>Sampſon</hi> aſleep vpon her knees,<note place="margin">Iudg. 16.19.</note> &amp; deliuereth him vp to the Philiſtins: this is that dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing daughter of <hi>Herodias,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Marke 6.25.</note> that cutteth off the head (the good beginnings) of many a <hi>Iohn Baptiſt.</hi> In a word, this is that talking damſell, at whoſe voice,<note place="margin">Luk. 22.56.57</note> with the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> we do moſt of vs denie our maiſter Chriſt. I may ſay truly in this caſe with that reuerend father, <hi>Crede mihi, loquor coram Domino,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſtin.</note> 
                  <hi>non mentior, Cedros Libani &amp; duces gregum ſub hac peſte cecidiſſe reperi, de quorum caſu non minùs dubitabam, quàm Ambroſii vel Hieronymi:</hi> Beleeue me, I ſpeake before the Lord, I lie not; I haue knowne the Cedars of Libanus, and the leaders of the flockes to haue fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len and ſunk downe violently vnder this temptation, of whoſe fall I made no more doubt then I did of the fall of <hi>Ambroſe</hi> or of <hi>Hierom.</hi> There being then in man a double pleaſure, <hi>carnis &amp; cordis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. ſerm. <hi>33.</hi> de verbis ſecundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Luca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> the pleaſure of the fleſh and the pleaſure of the heart; the pleaſure of the fleſh, when we giue our ſelues ouer to fulfill the luſts thereof; the pleaſure of the heart, when we delight our ſelues in the Lord: therefore the cariage of euery Chriſtian ſoule betweene theſe two pleaſures muſt be ſuch, that the pleaſure of the fleſh be no let
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:16325:22"/> or impediment to the pleaſure of the heart. But you wil ſay, how may this be, ſeeing there is continuall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie betweene theſe, and the one of them (as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaketh) ſtil luſteth againſt the other?<note place="margin">Gal. 5.17.</note> I anſwer affirmatiuely, that it may well be, and I will ſhew you how.<note place="margin">G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>egor. dialog. lib <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> I do reade in the writings of Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> this relation concerning one <hi>Benedict</hi> a religious man, that whenſoeuer he felt this conflict in his ſoule betweene the fleſh and the ſpirit, he would throng his body into a place where nettles and briers grew, <hi>&amp; ſic per vulne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra cutis, eduxitè corpore vulnus mentis,</hi> and ſo by thoſe wounds which he inflicted on his body, he cured that wound which would haue infected his ſoule: his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer inclination to fleſhly pleaſure by this ſtratageme being turned into paine and ſorrow. But if you think this to be too hard and ſharp a courſe for a carnal man to follow, I will then giue you a ſecond, which is of no leſſe conſequent then that, but yet of leſſe moleſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Toby</hi> in the ſixt chapter and ſecond verſe, when he wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed himſelfe in the floud Tigris, a great fiſh leaped at him to haue deuoured him, but by the Angels coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell hauing drawne the fiſh vnto drie land, it was ſo far from deuouring him, that it yeelded it ſelfe to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured of him. And ſo it falleth out in this conflict betweene the fleſh and the ſpirit: for this fleſh of ours ſo long as it ſwims in pleaſures, and is pampered vp with delicacies, ſo long is it ready to deuoure and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh our ſpirits: but if once we draw it vpon drie land from amidſt her pleaſures, by abſtinence and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, it will then haue no power, or at leaſt but ſmall power to impugne the ſpirit.<note place="margin">Gregor. Paſtor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urae. cap. <hi>42.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Olla ebulliens duplex ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet remedium, vel cum aqua frigida infunditur, vel cum
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:16325:22"/> ab igne elongatur:</hi> A ſeething pot hath but two reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, either thou muſt powre in cold water, or elſe thou muſt remoue it further from the fire: And ſo the vntamed fleſh of men boiling with luſt hath but two remedies, either they muſt powre into their ſoules the water of repentance, and allay the heat of their luſt with the cold teares of contrition, or elſe they muſt remoue it further fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fire; the fire I mean not only of meates and of drinkes (for gluttonie and drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe are the bellowes of concupiſcence,<note place="margin">Sine Cerere &amp; Baccho friget Venus &amp; ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mero aeſtuas ſpumat libidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem. Hieron.</note> and the belly boyling with wine fometh out luſt, as Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> ſaith) but alſo of laſciuious company, by which, as fire added vnto fire, the luſt of the fleſh is more intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate. Vnto this, if you pleaſe, as a meanes to reſtraine theſe luſtful paſſions, leaſt by them with the common multitude we be led from the wayes of life, I may add the fearfull end of this ſinne; fearfull I call it, not onely in regard of thoſe horrible diſeaſes breeding in the bodie, and in time conſuming euen the marrow in the bones; but fearfull in regard of that dreadfull iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which ſhall be inflicted in the laſt day both vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on body and ſoule in hell fire. For to the luſtful ſinner ſhall God ſay euen as the Angell ſaid to Babel,<note place="margin">Reuel. 18.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum glorificauit ſe in delicijs, tantum date illi tormentum &amp; luctum:</hi> In as much as he hath glorified himſelf and liued in pleaſure, ſo much giue you vnto him torment and ſorrow. There is a way that ſeemeth good, ſaith <hi>Salomon,</hi> but the end thereof is death: this way is the broad and common way of luſtfull fleſh and bloud, the pleaſures whereof though they be ſweet in the mouth, yet will they be bitter in the belly, like a cup of deadly poyſon. They are the daughters of thoſe lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſts
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:16325:23"/> mentioned in the Reuelation,<note place="margin">Reuel. 9.7.10.</note> which haue faces faire as men, but killing ſtings in their tailes: and I may well reſemble them to the herbe Sardonia in Sardinia, of which <hi>Solinus</hi> writeth, that it maketh the eaters thereof to looke as if they laughed, but in their laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they die. Much more might be added vnto this purpoſe, but (I take it) this may be ſufficient both to haue ſhewne you how theſe luſts of the fleſh are a great meanes to keepe many from the wayes of life, and alſo how we may repreſſe theſe luſts of the fleſh when they are rebellious. And now I come to the third and laſt enemy which oppoſeth himſelfe againſt man, and that is that old Serpent the Diuell, of whoſe ſubtilties in withdrawing vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wayes of life, as in the reſt, ſo in this I beſeech you to heare a while with patience.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Diuell.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 17.</note>As <hi>Amaleck</hi> reſiſted the Iſraelites, and vſed all the meanes that poſſibly he could deuiſe, to keep them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> coming into the earthly Canaan: ſo it is the policie of that infernall <hi>Amalek</hi> the diuell, to keepe men from comming into the Canaan of heauen. For the diuell hating God with a perfect hatred, and being not able to offer violence vnto him, he doth bend his force &amp; ſtrength againſt man, that ſo he may perſecute God in his creature. Saint <hi>Baſil</hi> reſembleth the rage and fury of the diuell in this point, vnto the rage &amp; fury of the wilde Panthers; for as they carrying naturally a hatred againſt man, if they ſee but the image and picture of a man, they run vpon it, and teare it in peeces, with no leſſe fury then if it were man himſelfe: ſo the diuell carrying a deadly hatred againſt God, becauſe his
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:16325:23"/> proud aſſaults were defeated by him, &amp; his arrogancy puniſhed with the loſſe of heauen and torment of hel, and being not able to do violence to God (as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe knoweth by wofull experience) he ſetteth vpon man, who is the picture or image of God, and he vſeth no leſſe cruelty both againſt his body and his ſoule, then he would (were he able) againſt God himſelfe. Our Sauiour Chriſt tels the Phariſees,<note place="margin">Math. 23.15.</note> that they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe ſea and land to make one of their profeſſion, that is, to make men ſuperſtitious, hypocriticall, ſinfull as themſelues were. That which our Sauiour obiecteth there againſt them, the diuel doth in a maner confeſſe of himſelfe.<note place="margin">Iob 1.7.</note> For when God asked him from whence he came, his anſwer was, that he came from compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the earth, and from walking to and fro in it. Now this walking of the diuel vp and downe in the earth, is not for any good which he intendeth vnto man, (for he walketh not as Chriſt did, to do good, and to heale all diſeaſes both of body and ſoule among the people) but as the end of the Phariſees co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſing of ſea &amp; land was to make men wicked like themſelues: ſo the end of the diuels compaſſing the earth is to draw men out of the wayes of life, and to make them damned like himſelfe. This was the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Peters</hi> meaning, when he giueth this reaſon of Satans compaſſing the earth,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.8.</note> 
                  <hi>He walketh about like a roring Lion ſeeking whom he may deuoure.</hi> Now among thoſe infinite meanes which the diuell vſeth to deuoure vs by drawing vs from the wayes of life, I will inſiſt briefly vpon theſe few. The firſt whereof is this, ſaith <hi>Bernard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The diuell doth ſubtilly pry,<note place="margin">Bernard. lib. de ordine vita.</note> and iudicially looke into the natures and complexions of men, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:16325:24"/> to the predominant and ouerruling humor in man, he applieth his temptation vnto this or that ſinne: (for in euery man there is ſome one humour that is moſt inclinable to ſome ſin.) As for example: The men of a ſanguin and bloudy complexion being naturally prone vnto ambition and vnchaſt behauior; the diuell ſtraight vpon this their naturall inclination will ſpend all his ſtrength to bring theſe men not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to an affecting, but alſo (if it be poſſible) to an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting of theſe ſins. You ſhall ſee it in the examples of king <hi>Dauid</hi> and his ſonne <hi>Abſolon.</hi> Firſt concerning <hi>Dauid,</hi> the diuell knowing that to be true which was ſaid of him,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 16.</note> that he was ruddy and of a good counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and obſeruing that he did dayly from the top of his houſe behold the wife of <hi>Vrias</hi> waſhing her; he preſently takes the occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſuggeſteth him to ſend for her; &amp; this being once done, he hath ſoone drawn <hi>Dauid</hi> out of the way of life, &amp; made him an adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer.<note place="margin">2. Sam. 14.</note> And for <hi>Abſolon</hi> his ſon, he being not vnlike vnto his father in that ſanguine and beautiful complexion; the diuell working vpon this, perſwadeth him to both to ambition and vncleane behauiour: for firſt he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades him to affect a kingdome, and rather then he ſhould be without a kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.</note> he puts this in his heart, to depriue his own father. And for vnchaſt behauior, ſo effectually did the diuell worke vpon him, that he, ſpared not his fathers concubines,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 16.</note> but defiled them, and himſelf with them, euen on the top of the houſe, in the ſight of all the people. And as the diuell prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth men of ſanguin complexions vnto theſe ſinnes, ſo he deales with men of other complexions; for if he finde that thou art flegmaticke, then wil he ſuggeſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:16325:24"/> thy ſoule the ſinne of idleneſſe, and prouoke thee vnto thoſe ſinnes that are depending vpon that. If he ſee thee to be cholericke, then he will perſwade thee to hatred, malice, anger, reuenge, and ſuch like. And if her perceiue thy complexion to be melancholick, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> will he bend all the power and ſtrength that he hath to driue thee to deſperation. To preuent therefore the diuell in this firſt policy, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith vnto the ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, <hi>Go to the Piſmire, ô thou ſluggard,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prouer. 6.6.</note> 
                  <hi>learne her wayes &amp; be wiſe;</hi> ſo ſay I vnto you: go vnto the diuel himſelf, learne his wayes and be wiſe. The diuels courſe (as you heare) is to looke diligently into the natures and complexions of men, and ſo to apply his temptations vnto thoſe ſinnes vnto which naturally they are carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: do thou then the like, looke carefully into thy own body, conſider diligently thy owne complexion, and withall thoſe ſinnes vnto which thou art naturally ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried: And if thou finde thy ſelfe naturally inclinable either vnto wantonneſſe, or vnto couetouſneſſe, or vnto wrath, or vnto enuy, or vnto drunkenneſſe, or vnto any one ſin more then other, be thou then ſure to ſet a barre before the doore of thy ſoule, and keepe Sathan from entring in: for ſinne,<note place="margin">Serm. de ſex tribulationibus</note> as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> well ſpeakes, by the ſuggeſtion of Sathan may ſtand at the doore of thy ſoule and knocke, but vnleſſe thou open vnto him by conſent, he cannot enter.</p>
               <p>A ſecond meanes which the diuell vſeth to keepe vs from the way of life is this: whereas our vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by the fall of <hi>Adam</hi> is already blind and darke, he corrupts it further, and maketh vs altogether vnable to diſcerne betweene good and euill, cauſing vs to commit wickedneſſe with this ſtrong conceit, that
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:16325:25"/> our actions and workes are iuſt. And hence it is, that ſo many in theſe dayes are ouertaken and deceiued with the ſinne of couetouſneſſe, becauſe though they be neuer ſo couetous,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 25.</note> yea as couetous as <hi>Naball</hi> was; yet the diuell perſwadeth them, and they eaſily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it, that it is not couetouſneſſe, it is but frugalitie. And he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce it is that we haue ſo many laſciuious people in the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d; becauſe though they be neuer ſo much giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the luſt of vncleanneſſe, yea to luſt after thoſe they ſhould not,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 13.</note> as <hi>Amnon</hi> did after his owne ſiſter <hi>Thamar,</hi> yet the diuell perſwadeth them, and they eaſily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it, that it is not to be called luſt, but rather loue. And thus our bad actions by the ſubtilty of the diuel being couered and coloured with good names, we are damned in theſe and in many other ſins, committing them and that with greedineſſe. But are we deſirous to preuent the diuell in this his ſecond policy? let vs then vſe the ſame diſcretion for the preſeruation of our ſoules, which we do for the preſeruation of our bodily health. It is a rule in Phiſick: <hi>Pars maxima ſani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis eſt notitia morbi:</hi> the beſt meanes for a ſicke man to recouer his health, is to acknowledge his ſickneſſe. For if a man which hath the gout in his toe, will not take notice of it, but ſay it is nothing but a tingling in his toe; and if a man hath got the cough of the lungs, and wil not acknowledge it, but ſay it is nothing but a great cold which he hath take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: theſe diſeaſes wil grow ſo hard vpon them, that at length it will be hard or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther impoſſible to cure them; wheras notice being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of them in time, the danger is the leſſe, &amp; the cure more eaſie. And ſo the Diuines haue the like rule: <hi>Pars maxima ſalutis eſt notitia peccati:</hi> The beſt meanes
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:16325:25"/> for a ſicke man in ſoule to be recouered, is to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and take notice of ſinne, which is the ſickneſſe of the ſoule. For the man that is ouergrowne with co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe, and ſaith it is but frugalitie: which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the ſinne of vncleanneſſe, and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth it to be but loue: the man who like a ſwaſhbuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler is alwayes drawing his ſword, cutting and hacking the harmeleſſe, and will haue this to haue no worſe name then manhood and fortitude: theſe and the like diſeaſes wil grow ſo hard vpon the ſoule, that it will be a plaine miracle to remoue them; whereas they being knowne and acknowledged for ſinnes, as they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, the cure of them is eaſie, and the danger of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing drawne out of the waies of life by them, is quickly auoided.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> But if the Diuell be thus preuented in this ſecond policie, then like a ſedulous and induſtrious enemie he ſetteth vpon vs with a third: for if he perceiue that thou conceiueſt aright of thy ſinnes, as that they are indeed ſinnes, then he laboureth to deceiue thee with this, that <hi>Dominus non videt;</hi> though thou takeſt them to be ſinnes, yet ſaith the diuell, the Lord doth not ſee them: and with this haue many bene deceiued. In the eighth of <hi>Ezechiel</hi> and twelfth verſe, it is Gods ſpeech vnto the Prophet: <hi>Son of man, haſt thou ſeene what the Ancients of Iſrael do in the darke, euery one in the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of his imagery? for they ſay, the Lord ſees vs not, the Lord hath forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth.</hi> Almighty God ſhews the Prophet, that the ancients of Iſrael had painted round about their walls euery ſimilitude of creeping things, and abhominable beaſts; and he makes this to be the cauſe, a groſſe perſwaſion that the Lord did not ſee
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:16325:26"/> them. But art thou deſirous to preuent the diuell in this fallacian alſo? then for thy better inſtruction let me reaſon with thee thus. He that could eſpie our firſt parents hiding themſelues among the thicke trees of the garden,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.9.</note> cannot his eyes find out thy ſinne, though it be committed in a ſecret place?<note place="margin">Pſal 94.9.</note> 
                  <hi>He that planted the eare, ſhall not he heare,</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid? or he that formed the eye, ſhall not he ſee?</hi> As if he had ſaid, Make no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, but whatſoeuer you ſpeake or do, God doth heare it, God doth ſee it. It is not with the ſight of God, as it is with the ſight of man: if there be not a due and a proportionate diſtance betweene the ſight of man and the obiect, the eye of man cannot poſſibly ſee it; but ſay God were circumſcribed in ſome one place, and grant it were in heauen, yet that great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance which is betweene heauen and earth, euen ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſcore and eighteene thouſand, foure hundred and ſixtie three miles, as the Aſtronomers haue coniectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; yet doth not this great diſtance hinder God from ſeeing our ſinnes.<note place="margin">Pſal. 14.2.</note> For <hi>the Lord looked downe from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vpon the children of men;</hi> what to do? <hi>to ſee if any would vnderſtand and ſeeeke after God:</hi> but looking downe he ſaw that all were gone out of the way, that there was none that did good, no not one.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> But if the Diuell preuaile not with this third falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, then behold a fourth: for doth God ſee thy ſin? (ſaith Sathan) yet be bold to ſinne ſtill, for God is ſo mercifull,<note place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſa. <hi>144.</hi>
                  </note> that he will not puniſh ſinne. It is Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtines</hi> complaint, that there be two ſorts of men which do ſnatch occaſions of ſinning to themſelues, the one from the mercie, the other from the iuſtice of God. One ſaith, God will take ſo ſtrict and ſeuere an
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:16325:26"/> account of our doings, that we ſhall not be able to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer one for a thouſand; and therefore (ſaith he) being ſure to be damned, <hi>cur non facio quiquid volo?</hi> why do I not whatſoeuer I wil? The other, he ſaith Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie is aboue his workes, and at what time ſoeuer I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, though it be at the laſt gaſpe, he wil receiue me with the armes of his mercy, as he did the theefe vpon the croſſe; and therefore why do not I go on ſtill in my wickedneſſe? <hi>Deſperat ille vt peccet, ſperat iſte vt peccet, vtrum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> metuendum:</hi> the one deſpaireth, that he may ſinne ſtill, the other hopeth, that he may ſinne ſtill, and both are to be feared. But for thoſe which dreame altogether of Gods mercie, that this fallacian of the diuels (by which many thouſands are drawne from the wayes of life) may be preuented, let them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that God, as he is mercifull, ſo he is iuſt. In the 116. Pſalme and fifth verſe, <hi>The Lord is mercifull and iuſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid;</hi> not mercifull alone, but iuſt alſo. And as we cannot bide our ſinnes from the all-ſeeing eye of God: ſo we cannot be defended fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſtrong arme of his iuſtice. In the 6. of <hi>Geneſis</hi> and 12. verſe, it is ſaid that God looked downe vpon the earth, and ſeeing that all fleſh had corrupted his wayes, he ſaith to <hi>Noah, An end of al fleſh is come before me, for the earth is filled with crueltie through them, and behold I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them from the earth.</hi> In which words we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue firſt that God ſees our ſinnes; ſecondly, that though he ſeeth ſinne, yet he is mercifull; and thirdly, that as he is mercifull, ſo he is iuſt. God looked downe vpon the earth, and ſaw that all fleſh had corrupted his way, there is the firſt, Gods ſight of ſinne: the earth is filled with crueltie, there is the ſecond, the mercie
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:16325:27"/> of God and long ſuffering: for he doth not preſently execute iudgement vpon them, but ſtayed ſo long till the earth was full of crueltie. <hi>And behold I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them from the earth,</hi> there is Gods iuſtice.</p>
               <p>But if the diuell by none of theſe be able to deceiue vs, and to draw vs from the wayes of life, then he hath a fift, which ſhall be my laſt at this time. He ſetteth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes the good and pleaſure that doth accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany our ſinne; and indeede theſe are ſhrewd tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions vnto fleſh and blood.<note place="margin">Pſal. 133.1.</note> The Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth choiſe of theſe two to draw vs vnto brotherly loue and vnity: O how good and pleaſant a thing it is, for brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to dwel together in vnity: And ſo the diuel he maketh choiſe of both theſe to draw vs to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of iniquity, ſometimes vſing but one of theſe, and ſometimes ioyning them both for the ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his temptation. In the 22. of Numbers one of theſe was ſufficient to draw <hi>Balaam</hi> vnto ſinne: for though he had receiued a commandement from God that he ſhould not go with the princes of Moab to curſe the people of Iſrael; yet when he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered that <hi>Balacks</hi> offers would proue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modious to him, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolueth vpon the iourney with them, and his Aſſes thriſe reuolt could not ſtay him. But in the third of Geneſis there the diuell vſeth both, and with them both he preuailed againſt our mother <hi>Eue;</hi> for albeit ſhe knew well, that ſhe ſhould dye the death in eating of the forbidden tree, yet becauſe ſhe ſaw that it was good for meat, and pleaſant to the eyes, ſhe tooke thereof and did eate. That then theſe deceitful temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of the diuel may be reiected: firſt that no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity do draw thee from the wayes of life to ſinne,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:16325:27"/> let that ſaying of our Sauiour Chriſt be alwaies in thy mind; what ſhal a man get if he win the whole world,<note place="margin">Math. 16.26.</note> and looſe his owne ſoule? what ſhall a man get if by vſury, oppreſſion of the poore, extortio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, falſe weights, falſe meaſures, and the like, he ſhall be able to purchaſe much land,<note place="margin">Luk. 16.19.</note> and with the rich glutton go in purple and fine linnen, and fare deliciouſly euery day; when as theſe commodious ſinnes as he accounteth them, ſhall bring no leſſe diſcommoditie vpon him then hel fire? And ſecondly that no pleaſure preuail with thee, reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that ſin, though it be ſweet in the mouth, yet it wil be bitter in the belly; that though it be pleaſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in the beginning, yet it will be painfull in the end: &amp; that the diuell dealeth herein with vs, as vnconſcionable Mercers and Drapers deale with their chapmen. For as they neuer ſhew vnto their chapmen the middle part &amp; fag end of their wares, which perhaps are ſtark naught, but onely the vpper part thereof which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly is very good: ſo this maiſter Mercer the diuel, he ſheweth alwaies to his ſinfull chapmen the vpper part of his wares, namely the preſent pleaſure, delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and delight of ſin; but as for the middle part of his wares, which is remorſe of conſcience, and the fag end of his wares which is Gods vengeance, theſe he neuer ſheweth. For (beloued) if men ſhould ſee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand with the ſpirituall eyes of their ſoules, either the middle part of ſinne, which is remorſe of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, or the end of ſinne which is Gods vengeance, either in this life, or in the other; then out of doubt, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the diuel ſhal offer his wares vnto the ſale, (as to the couetous man his neighbors vineyard, to the adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer his neighbors wife, to the taylour long bils, to the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:16325:28"/> retailer falſe weights, and ſo in the reſt) they will all anſwer, (if there be any ſparke of grace or goodneſſe in them) as the Athenian Orator did vpon the like proffer; <hi>Non emam tanti poenitere,</hi> I wil not buy repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance ſo deare. And thus at laſt haue you ſeene thoſe impediments and lets why ſo few do finde the way of life. The impediments <hi>ex parte quaerentis,</hi> in our ſelues that ſeeke the way are three, blindneſſe of reaſon, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſneſſe of will, and want of perſeuerance: and the lets <hi>ex parte retrahentium</hi> are three likewiſe; the world with his inticements, the fleſh with her allurements, and the diuell with his ſuggeſtions vnto ſinne. And now to conclude,<note place="margin">Hom. <hi>1.</hi> ad pop. Antioch.</note> Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> in his firſt homily to the people of Antioch, doth require a reward for a ſermon which he made againſt the blaſphemers of Gods name. The onely reward (beloued) which I wil craue for my ſermon, is this, that it would pleaſe Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, ſo to worke in the hearts of all you that haue now bene partakers of it, that you may ſay, and ſay truly of my ſermon, as <hi>Tully</hi> in his Academicks ſaith of <hi>Varros</hi> bookes: <hi>Nos in noſtra vrbe peregrinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes tanquam hoſpites, tui libri quaſi domum deduxerunt;</hi> We who heretofore in this our city of London, by the blindneſſe of our reaſon, the peruerſneſſe of our wils, and want of perſeuerance, haue erred from the wayes of life, and by the inticements of the world, the allurements of the fleſh, and the ſuggeſtions of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, haue wandered vp and downe in the plaines of ſinne, and in the vallies of iniquitie, are thereby now brought home againe vnto the wayes of life, and reduced into the number of that little flocke, whereof that great Shepheard and Biſhop of our
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:16325:28"/> ſoules, Chriſt Ieſus is the head. The which God the Father grant for his Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, to whom with the bleſſed ſpirit, three in Trinitie but one in Vnitie, be aſcribed all honour and glorie for euermore.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:16325:29"/>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:16325:29"/>
            <head>THE LAST IVDGEMENT.</head>
            <div type="dedication">
               <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL IOHN BREVVSTER ESQVIRE.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, among many patrons of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and Theologicall endeuours, I preſume to rank your name; who as I know you not inferiour to the beſt, for a Fautor of learning and a louer of Pietie; ſo I preſent you here with ſuch a worke beſt fitting your addiction, and moſt worthie your patronage. And howſoeuer I may ſeeme officiouſly bold to publiſh theſe things without free conſent of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor (as I confeſſe I do:) yet out of earneſt deſire to raiſe him from obſcuritie to a deſerued eminence in the worlds ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and throughly moued with pitie, that ſo heauenly things ſhould periſh with the breath they were deliuered, (as if eternitie ſhould fade with a moment:) I haue aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured to giue them longer life, ſeconding my boldneſſe
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:16325:30"/> with a ſtrong preſumption, that I ſhall fruſtrate needleſſe doubts, and herein deſerue your good opinion. And on this hope I rest, committing the ſequele to your ſerious view, and my attempt in this to your fauourable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours in all affection and dutie, <hi>C. B.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:16325:30"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MATTH. 25.15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Watch therefore, for you know neither the day nor the houre when the Sonne of man will come.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S when children hauing ouer-ſlept themſelues, and begin to cry, as fearing the correction of their ſeuere maiſters; their indulgent mothers do common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly comfort them with one of theſe two things, as firſt, that there is no time yet paſt, and ſecondly, that their maiſter is a gentle man and will forgiue them: In the very ſame manner do the carnall and careleſſe worldlings of this age deale with thoſe their acquaintance and friends, who haue fetched a long and a deepe ſleepe in ſinne and ſecuritie. For whereas their counſell to them ſhould be that which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> hath, <hi>Epheſ. 5.14. Awake thou that ſleepeſt, and ſtand vp fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dead, and Chriſt ſhall giue thee light:</hi> theſe men cleane contrary, to take away all feare of iudgement to come in a ſinner, they apply either one or both theſe comforts to them; firſt, that <hi>nullum tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus poenitentiae inidoneum,</hi> that no time is too late to come vnto God by repentance: and if they ſtagger in their hope notwithſtanding this firſt comfort, then is it commonly backed with this ſecond, that God is <hi>Deus miſericordiae,</hi> a God of mercie, and will forgiue them. And in this for the moſt part we are all like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Benhadad, 2. King. 20.</hi> For as he fled from the King
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:16325:31"/> of Iſrael from place vnto place, till he was forced into a chamber; and when he could go no farther, thus he was comforted, <hi>Reges Iſrael ſunt Reges miſericordes,</hi> The Kings of Iſrael are mercifull Kings. So men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly when they are in health and ſtrength of bodie, they run on in iniquitie and ſinne, and are impiouſly rebellious againſt the holy one of Iſrael: but when they are chaſed as it were into their chambers either by ſickneſſe or old age, and when there is no way but one, as we ſay, but death with them; then this is their comfort, that <hi>Deus Iſrael eſt Deus miſericordiae,</hi> that the God of Iſrael wil be then vnto them a God of mercy. But (beloued) let vs neither flatter our ſelues with vaine hopes, nor deceiue our neighbours with falſe comforts; for though God accepteth of him who co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vnto him in his old age which is the euening of his life (as you may ſee by him who had a penie giuen him, <hi>Math. 20.9.</hi> though he came at the end of the day to the vineyard, and by the theefe <hi>(Luke 25.43.)</hi> who was poſted euen from the croſſe vnto Paradiſe;) yet God had rather thou ſhouldeſt come vnto him in thy youth, which is the morning of thy age. And to that end ſaith the wiſe man, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Remember now thy Creator in the dayes of thy youth:</hi> leaſt our comming vnto God ſhould be put off and deferred, he ſaith, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member now:</hi> and leaſt we ſhould put off till old age or death, he addeth <hi>in the dayes of thy youth.</hi> And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rely if there were no other reaſon for it, or if we had not the lamentable example of the fiue fooliſh virgins in this chapter to direct vs; who calling, <hi>Lord, Lord, open vnto vs,</hi> when it was too late, were ſhut out and exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the kingdome of heauen: yet this may be
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:16325:31"/> ſufficient, that we ſee commonly in our experience carnall and careleſſe ſinners,<note place="margin">Juſto Dei iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictio hac poena punitur pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, vt mortens obliuiſcatur ſui qui cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> viueret oblitus eſt Dei. Auguſtin.</note> by the iuſt iudgement of God, to be puniſhed with this kinde of puniſhment; namely in old age and at the houre of death to forget both themſelues and God, as before in their youth they had no care to remember him. And for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond comfort, that God is <hi>Deus miſericordiae,</hi> a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull God: ſure it is, that as the women ſung concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Dauid, 1. Sam. 18.7. Saul hath ſlaine his thouſand, but Dauid his te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thouſands:</hi> So we may ſorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſing and ſay truly, that the deſpaire of Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie hath ſlaine thouſands, but the groſſe preſumption of his mercie hath ſlaine ten thouſands, it hath ſent ten times as many more vnto hell as the deſpaire of his mercie. And therefore let vs not ſuffer our ſelues any longer to be deceiued; for as it is true of God which the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> hath, Pſalm. 86.15. that the Lord is a pitifull God, mercifull, ſlow to anger, and great in kindneſſe, (for all theſe doth be heape toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in that verſe:) yet haue we no reaſon to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous vpon theſe his mercies, but we ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther looke backe vnto the 18. Pſalme and 26. verſe, where the Prophet ſpeaking of God, he ſaith thus; <hi>With the pure thou wilt ſhew thy ſelfe pure, and with the froward thou wilt ſhew thy ſelfe froward:</hi> that is, as he wil mercifully receiue and pardon thoſe that are penitent, ſo he will iuſtly repell and ſeuerely puniſh thoſe that are impenitent. In the verſes which go before from the beginning of this Chapter, we haue the truth and proofe of this doctrine in the parable of the ten vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins: For as we ſee the fiue wiſe virgins who had oyle in their lampes, that is, whoſe good workes and godly
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:16325:32"/> liues did ſhine and giue light vnto others, as a lampe giues light vnto thoſe that are in darkneſſe; as we ſee theſe moſt mercifully to be receiued, and to enter in with the bridegroome: ſo the fiue fooliſh virgins, who did ſlumber and ſleepe, and had no care to expect the bridegroomes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming by a vertuous and godly life, thoſe we ſee moſt iuſtly to be ſhut out. And our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt concludeth and ſhutteth vp that parable with this comfortable &amp; ſweet caueat vnto vs: <hi>Watch therefore, for you know neither the day nor the houre when the Sonne of man will come.</hi> As if he ſhould haue ſaid, ſeeing there will be a comming of the Sonne of man to iudgement; and his comming, as it wil be ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and comfortable to the godly, ſo it will be fearfull and terrible to the wicked, and we know neither the day nor the houre when he wil come: therfore ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber not, ſleepe not, be not careleſſe, be not ſecure in your ſinnes, but watch, that is, be prepared by a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and godly life againſt his comming; that ſo when he ſhal come, you may be receiued into heauen with the fiue wiſe virgins, and not be excluded and ſhut out of heauen with the fiue fooliſh. <hi>Watch ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, for you know neither the day nor the houre when the Sonne of man will come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the right opening &amp; handling of which words, I beſeech you to obſerue carefully with me theſe foure particular conſiderations. Firſt, that there will be a comming of the Sonne of man to iudgement: <hi>He wil come.</hi> Secondly that becauſe he commeth to iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, therfore his comming wil be fearful &amp; terrible. Thirdly that the time of his fearfull and terrible com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vnto iudgement is vncertaine: <hi>We neither know
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:16325:32"/> the day nor the houre when he wil come.</hi> And laſtly the vſe which we are to make of all theſe; &amp; this is a careful &amp; vigilant preparation of our ſelues againſt his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, in the firſt words, <hi>Vigilate igitur, Watch therefore. Watch therefore, for you know neither the day nor the houre when the Sonne of man will come.</hi> Now of all theſe in their order. And firſt for the firſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That there wil be a comming of the Sonne of man to iudgement. <hi>He will come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was the fond opinion of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> that great Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, that the world had no beginning,<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> de coelo cap. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> and ſo conſequently ſhall haue no end; and that mankind with all other creatures in the world, were alwayes, and ſhould be alwayes. The which opinion of his if it were true, then might men lawfully doubt, whether there ſhould be a general Seſſions, a generall calling or no, of men vnto iudgement. But the beſt way to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute a heathen, is by a heathen.<note place="margin">Plinius Secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus. Auguſt. de ciu. dei. lib. <hi>15.</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> It was therfore the true ſentence of another heathen man, that the older the world waxeth, the bodies of men naturally, for ſtature are leſſe, and for ſtrength are weaker; and this was the opinion of <hi>Homer</hi> himſelfe a great Poet, and no ſmall Philoſopher. For ſpeaking of the battell which was fought betweene <hi>Aeneas</hi> and <hi>Diomedes,</hi> he affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that <hi>Diomedes</hi> caſt a ſtone at <hi>Aeneas,</hi> ſo heauy and of ſo great a weight, as fourteen men (ſaith he) are not able to caſt the like, as men go now a dayes. And if as the world waxeth in yeares, ſo mans ſtrength doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, then doubtleſſe the world waxing ſtill old, it will at laſt come to nothing; and ſo conſequently euen in plaine reaſon, the world and men in the world will
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:16325:33"/> haue an end. But me thinks I heare ſome godleſſe and prophane Atheiſt reply thus. Suppoſe that the world and men in the world ſhall haue an end; yet I am of opinion that there is the ſame end of a man that there is of a beaſt. A beaſt, when it dieth, the fleſh is conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and the ſoule vaniſheth into the aire, and there is his full period: and why may it not be ſo with man? For the anſwer herunto: It was <hi>Plato</hi> his opinion (who deſerued and that iuſtly, the name of a diuine) that the ſoules of men did not die, but liue, being ſeparated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their bodyes, and that after this life ended they ſhould giue an account of all their actions. And thoſe fictions in the Poets, concerning the Eliſian fields and places of pleaſure for good men after this life, and places of puniſhment for euil men; what did they elſe ſhew, but that there hath bene among the wiſeſt of the heathen a certaine perſwaſion of the ſoules immortality, and that after this life it ſhould be iudged? But becauſe the prophane Atheiſt wil not be drawne to a beleef, either of the ſoules immortality, or of the bodies reſurrection in the day of iudgment, vnleſſe we can win them ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by the maine ſway of reaſon, let vs ſee whether in reaſon we commit any abſurdity or no, in beleeuing the reſurrection of the body. <hi>Tertullian</hi> propounding the queſtion for them:<note place="margin">In Apol. cap. <hi>45</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quomodo diſſoluta materia ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hiberi poteſt?</hi> How is it poſſible that the matter of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s body being once diſſolued, as it ſhall be in the graue, ſhould euer riſe againe, and be perfectly exhibited be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the iudgement ſeat of God? he doth anſwer their queſtion thus: <hi>Quid tibi noui eueniet? qui non eras, fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus es, &amp; cum iterum non eris, fies:</hi> What ſtrange or new wonder is this? thou which once wert not, waſt
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:16325:33"/> made by God, and ſo hereafter when thou ſhalt not be, thou ſhalt be made again; for God can as eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore thee being diſſolued into duſt, as he could cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate thee at the firſt being nothing. In the firſt Pſalme &amp; fifth verſe we reade it thus. <hi>The wicked ſhall not ſtand in iudgement:</hi> but the Caldey paraphraſe hath it thus, <hi>They ſhal not riſe in that great day, the day of iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</hi> In regard of which words, ſome Hebrew writers haue bene bold to make this collection, that the wicked ſhal not riſe, but their bodies and ſoules at the houre of death ſhall periſh and come to nothing. But as in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny points they are fantaſtically fooliſh: ſo in this are they moſt erroneouſly hereticall. For although it be there ſaid, that the wicked ſhal not riſe in iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, we muſt not thereby gather, <hi>Carere eos reſurgendi natura, ſed reſurgendi in iudicium perdidiſſe ordinem:</hi> We muſt not gather, that the nature &amp; property of riſing ſhal be wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but that they haue loſt the order of ri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſing vnto iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Now what the order of riſing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is, we may ſee in the third of <hi>Ioh.</hi> the 18. &amp; 19. ver. where our Sauiour ſaith thus. <hi>He that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth in me ſhall not be iudged, but he which beleeueth not, Iam iudicatus eſt, he is already iudged.</hi> The which words of our Sauiour, haply they may trouble the careleſſe hearers, and the negligent readers therof; for in that he ſaith, <hi>he that beleeueth in me ſhall not be iudged,</hi> there he exempteth the faithful from iudgment: and in that he ſaith, <hi>he that beleeueth not, is already iudged,</hi> he ſeemes to teach that the Infidels ſhal not be admitted vnto iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And if the faithfull are exempted fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to come, and the Infidels are already iudged; why then, <hi>Non videtur locus eſſe relictus iudicio,</hi> It ſhould
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:16325:34"/> ſeeme there is no place left for iudgement, and that there are no perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to be iudged. Yes ſaith <hi>Hilary;</hi> for in the 18. verſe, our Sauior hauing exe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted the beleeuers and vnbeleeuers; the beleeuers <hi>à iudicio condemnatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> from the iudgement of condemnation: and the Infidels and vnbeleeuers, becauſe their iudgement of condemnation is ſo certain, that it is in the eternall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of God already paſt, and there remaines onely at the laſt day but the publication thereof. In the 19. verſe he expreſſeth the parties to be iudged, and the cauſe of their iudgement; for thus he ſaith: <hi>This is the condemnation, that light is come into the world, and men loued darkeneſſe rather then the light, becauſe their deeds are euill.</hi> As if he had ſaid: There is a middle ſort of people, which are neither altogether without faith, nor abſolutely faithfull; the feare of God contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth them in the Church, but the vaine vanities of the world draw them vnto ſecular vices, <hi>Orant quia timent, peccant quia volunt,</hi> they pray becauſe they are afraid of God and his iudgements, but withall they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſinne, becauſe they take a pleaſure and delight in it. Theſe then which do loue darkeneſſe rather then light, that is, which are content to loue Chriſt who is the light of the world, but withall they preferre the euill deeds of darkneſſe, theſe are they (let the Hebrew writers fable what they wil) which ſhal one day come to iudgement. And that we may the better conceiue, and beleeue this; there are as you know, in our aſſiſes and ſeſſions here vpon earth, certaine things neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly required. As firſt, there is required the perſon and preſence of the Iudge. Secondly, certaine vpright Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices his aſſiſtants vpon the bench. Thirdly, the citati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:16325:34"/> of the priſoners to the bar, with leaue giuen them to pleade for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues. Fourthly, the allegation or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the witneſſes. Fiftly, the Iudges verdit. Sixt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the proceeding to ſentence either of abſolution or condemnation. And laſtly the execution of the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to the ſheriffe or bayliffe. Of al which (beloued) that we may the better beleeue that great ſeſſions in that laſt and dreadfull day of iudgement, we haue ſpeciall mention in the Scriptures. And firſt for the Iudge, that is Ieſus Chriſt the ſecond perſon in Trinitie. Forhowſoeuer the whole Trinitie haue a ſtroke in the action, yet the execution thereof is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by them to the ſecond perſon. So Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſaith (<hi>Iohn</hi> the 5.22.) <hi>The Father iudgeth no man, but hath commited all iudgement to the Sonne.</hi> So Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith (Rom. 14.10.) <hi>We muſt all of vs appeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for the iudgement ſeat of Chriſt.</hi> And Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> giueth a reaſon of it thus, <hi>Vt ea natura iudicem agat, quae ſub iudice ſtetit,</hi> That he may act the office of a iudge in that nature in which he ſtood before a iudge. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, for his aſſiſtants vpon the bench, they are his diſciples (<hi>Math.</hi> 19.28.) <hi>For when the ſonne of man</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>ſhall ſit in the throne of his maieſtie, yee which haue followed me in the regeneration, ſhall ſit alſo vpon twelue thrones, and iudge the twelue tribes of Iſrael.</hi> And thirdly, for the bringing of the priſoners to the bar, yee haue it in the 5. of <hi>Iohn</hi> and 28. verſ. <hi>The houre ſhall come in which all that are in the graues ſhall heare the voice of the ſonne of God, and they ſhal come forth that haue done good vnto the reſurrection of life, but they which haue done euill vnto the reſurrection of condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> At which time the priſoner ſhall haue free liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:16325:35"/> to ſpeake what he can for himſelfe; for ſo they on the left hand pleade not guilty (<hi>Math.</hi> 25.44.) <hi>Lord when haue we ſeene thee an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gred, or athirſt, or a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, or naked, or ſicke, or in priſon, &amp; did not miniſter vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee?</hi> And fourthly, for the witneſſes, they are more then two. For firſt Chriſt who is the Iudge, he will witneſſe againſt vs. <hi>Ier.</hi> 29.23. <hi>Ego ſum iudex &amp; teſtis, I am both a iudge and a witneſſe.</hi> And whereas men are often compelled and enforced to beare witneſſe to the truth; in the third of <hi>Malachy</hi> and fift verſe: <hi>Ego ſum teſtis velox,</hi> I am a ſwift witneſſe. And if Chriſt ſhould faile in his teſtimonie againſt vs, yet his law-giuer <hi>Moſes</hi> wil not faile; for ſo Chriſt ſaith (<hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.45.) <hi>Do not thinke that I will accuſe you to my Father: there is one that accuſeth you, euen</hi> Moſes <hi>in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you truſt.</hi> And though Chriſt and <hi>Moſes</hi> both do faile in their wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, yet is there another who will not be wanting, euen the diuell, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many haue truſted too much. For in the 12. of the Reuel. 10. v. Sathan the accuſer of the brethren is caſt downe, who <hi>accuſeth</hi> them before God day and night. And thus, ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> will he vrge in the laſt day and enforce his accuſation before God. Thine they were O king of heauen by creation, but mine they are by tranſgreſſion. <hi>Tui per gratiam quam amiſerunt, mei per culpam in qua deceſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt:</hi> Thine they were by grace, which wilfully they haue caſt away, mine they are by ſins, which hath caſt them away: thine they were by the glorious merit of thy paſſion, mine they are for want of charitable compaſſion: thine they were becauſe thou diedſt for their ſins, mine they they are becauſe they died not, but liued vnto ſin. <hi>Nobis ergo aſſocientur in poenis qui co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formati
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:16325:35"/> ſunt in culpis:</hi> and therfore ô ſupreme iudge, it ſtands with equitie &amp; iuſtice, that theſe ſhold be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers in our puniſhments, who while they liued in the world, were companions in our ſinnes. But if Chriſt, and <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the diuel ſhould faile in their witneſſe, though neither of theſe did know of thy ſinne, and ſo conſequently could not iuſtly accuſe thee; yet as <hi>Lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantius</hi> well ſaith, <hi>Quid prodeſt tibi non habere conſcium, habenti conſcientia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</hi> What will the ignorance of others auaile thee, when as the teſtimony of thy owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience wil preuaile againſt thee? For as there are ſome which haue a good conſcience (Heb. 13.18.) ſo there are others which haue a bad conſcience, a conſcience ſeared with a hot iron (1. <hi>Timoth.</hi> 4.4.) And as they who in godly pureneſſe and not in fleſhly wiſedome, haue their conuerſation in this world, the teſtimony of their conſcience ſhal cauſe them to reioyce (1. Cor. 1.12.) ſo they which haue followed the vaine pleaſures, &amp; the pleaſing vanities of this world, the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of their conſcience ſhall cauſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to lament. And then a mans owne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience acccuſing him, there needeth no iury to be impannelled: for the party con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing the action, the Iudge will immediatly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to ſentence, the which ſentence ſhall not be (like the Roman<note n="*" place="margin">Romani ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellas ſeu lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras in vrnam ſolebant conij<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere: literae fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. A.C. A lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra Abſolutio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, C litera condemnatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis: talis in iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cijs conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo apud Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> reſpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debat Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum C. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Romanorum. A.</note> A) a ſentence of Abſolution, whereof mention is made (<hi>Math.</hi> 25.34) <hi>Venite benedicti, Come ye bleſſed of my Father, inherit the kingdome prepared for you from the foundation of the world.</hi> But it ſhall be (like that <hi>nigrum</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of the Greeks) a ſentence of condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, whereof mention is made in the ſame chapter and 41. verſe. <hi>Ite maledicti, Go ye curſed into euerlaſting fire, which is prepared for the diuell and his Angels.</hi> And
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:16325:36"/> then laſt of all followeth the executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſentence, the charge whereof ſhall be committed to the Angels. For ſo ſaith our Sauiour (<hi>Math.</hi> 13.49.) <hi>At the end of the world, the Angels ſhal go forth, and ſeuer the bad from among the iuſt, and ſhall caſt them into a fornace of fire, where ſhall be wailing and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi> So then to conclude this with that of the Preacher (Eccl. 11.9.) <hi>Reioyce ô young man in thy youth, let thy heart cheere thee in the dayes of thy youth, walke in the wayes of thy heart, and in the luſts of thine owne eyes; but yet know that for all theſe things God ſhall bring thee vnto iudgement.</hi> Be not therefore deceiued, neither flatter your ſelues with this vaine imagination, that though you commit ſinne with greedineſſe, yet there will be no reckoning and account for it. Say not within your ſelues, as it is in the 5. of Eccle. 4. I haue ſinned and what euill hath come vnto me? For as it followeth in the ſame place, <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus eſt</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Patiens red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor dicitur, quia peccata homin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m &amp; patitur &amp; red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. Nam quos Diu vt conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantur to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerat, non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſos duriùs damnat. Greg. Hom. <hi>13.</hi> in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uang.</note> 
               <hi>patiens redditor: The Lord is a patient rewarder;</hi> that is, as he is patient for a time and expecteth thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne from ſinne; ſo he is a rewarder, &amp; will not leaue thee vnpuniſhed. <hi>Lento gradu ad vindictam ira diuina procedit, ſed tarditatem ſupplicij grauitate iudicij recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſat;</hi> The iuſtice of God goes ſlowly indeed, but it recompenſeth the ſlackneſſe of iudgement with the heauineſſe thereof. And therefore as <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaid vnto the rich man, (<hi>Luke</hi> 16.25.) <hi>Hîc bona, ſed illîc ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la,</hi> Here thou receiuedſt good things, but now thou art tormented: ſo haply without any checke or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trolement, thou maieſt follow thy ſinfull pleaſures and delights here in this world; but there will one day come a time, when for thoſe thou ſhalt be brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Iudge, and the iudge ſhall deliuer thee to a iay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:16325:36"/> and the iaylour ſhall caſt thee into priſon, from whence thou ſhalt neuer be releaſed. And therefore howſoeuer there hath heretofore bene no impreſſion in our hearts of this iudgement to come, yet hereafter as Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> confeſſeth of himſelfe, <hi>ſiue comedas, ſiue bibas,</hi> whether thou eateſt or drinkeſt, whether thou wakeſt or ſleepeſt, whether thou walkeſt abroad or ſtayeſt at home, let that be euer ſounding in thy eares, which was euer ſounding in his eares: <hi>Surgite mortui, venite ad iudicium:</hi> Ariſe ô you dead, and come to iudgement. Thus much for the firſt conſideration: That there will be a comming of the Sonne of man to iudgement. I come to the ſecond.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That this his comming vnto Iudgement will be terrible.</p>
            <p>In the ninth of <hi>Eſay</hi> and ſixt verſe, the Prophet ſpeaking of the coming of our Sauior Chriſt, he ſaith thus: <hi>Paruulus natus eſt nobis: A child is borne vnto vs, and his name ſhall be called Wonderful, Counſeller, the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting Father, the Prince of peace:</hi> and in the 21. of <hi>Matthew</hi> and fift verſe, there is the propheſie fulfilled, <hi>Ecce Rex tuus venit tibi manſuetus: Tel ye the daughter of Sion, Behold thy King commeth vnto thee meek.</hi> But that ſetteth out his firſt coming: but now we are to lay ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his ſecond comming. Then he came in humilitie, but now we are to ſpeake of his comming in glorie. Then he came like milde and little <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 17.</note> to free vs from the Diuel that great <hi>Goliah;</hi> but hereafter he wil come like angry and armed <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 25.</note> againſt ingratefull <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bals.</hi> Then he came with comforts in his right hand; for he came not to call the righteous,<note place="margin">Math. 9.13. Iohn 5.29.</note> but ſinners to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance: but hereafter he ſhall come with terrour in
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:16325:37"/> his left hand, for he ſhall call the vnrepentant ſinners vnto iudgement. Then, that the world might be cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified vnto vs, and we vnto the world, Chriſt Ieſus vouchſafed to be crucified in the world: but hereafter becauſe the preaching of Chriſt his croſſe is accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted fooliſhneſſe by the wicked world, therefore Ieſus Chriſt wil come to crucifie the world. Then the people ſhouted,<note place="margin">Mat. 21.9. Mat. 24.30.</note> and diſtinctly cried <hi>Hoſanna</hi> for ioy, but hereafter the wicked ſhall yell &amp; make a confuſed noiſe for feare; yea ſo fearfull wil this his ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vnto iudgement be, that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> diſputing of it before <hi>Felix,</hi> (as I now before you) it made the very heart of <hi>Felix</hi> to tremble. Act. 24.26. And no maruell, for if that firſt apparition of God was ſo fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and terrible to the people of the Iewes (Exodus 20.18.) that <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelfe ſaid, <hi>I feare and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble;</hi> and the people fled, and ſtood a farre off, and ſayd to <hi>Moſes, Talke thou with vs, and we will heare; but let not God talke with vs, least we die:</hi> how fearfull then and terrible will his ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming be? For at that firſt appearing he came onely to giue them lawes; but at this ſecond he will come to puniſh the tranſgreſſors of his lawes.<note place="margin">Heſt. 15.10.</note> Surely if <hi>Heſter</hi> fell vpon the ground, and life for a time went out at the gates of her body, when ſhe beheld the maieſtie of <hi>Aſſuerus</hi> the King:<note place="margin">Dan. 8.17.</note> if <hi>Daniel</hi> in the eight chapter of his propheſie, at the ſight of an Angell trembled and was ſore afraid:<note place="margin">Mat. 28.4.</note> if the keepers of the ſepulcher in the day of our Sauiour his reſurrection, were terrified and became as dead men: if the Iewes comming armed into the garden to apprehend Ieſus,<note place="margin">Iohn 18.6.</note> when they heard him but ſay, <hi>Ego ſum, I am the man;</hi> if they fell back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:16325:37"/> vpon the ground, and became as dead men: O then what ſhall miſerable men and women do, when they ſhall ſee Ieſus Chriſt not yeelding vp his body to be puniſhed by ſinners as then, but comming in the clouds with power and great glorie to puniſh ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners?<note place="margin">Luke 21.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Indeede if there were the ſame meanes and ſuch hopes of preſeruing men fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the iudgement to come, as there are of preuenting iudgement and iuſtice here vpon the earth, then the feare thereof were altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther needleſſe: but you ſhall ſee the caſe is farre diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent. For firſt, here vpon earth when men ſtand vpon life and death, interceſſion is made by others for the procurement of their deliuery: yea oftentimes ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in commendation of the priſoner are admitted by the bench;<note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> for ſo was the cuſtome among the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, till the law of <hi>Pompey</hi> tooke it away. But in the day of the laſt iudgement, there will be no place for interceſſion,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 14. 1 Sam. 25</note> there ſhall then be no <hi>Ioab</hi> to intreate for <hi>Abſolom,</hi> there ſhall then be no <hi>Abigail</hi> to ſpeake for <hi>Nabal.</hi> The truth of which doctrine is moſt euident in the Scriptures: for looke into the 22. of <hi>Matthew</hi> and 13. verſe, and you ſhall there ſee, that the partie that had not on a wedding garment, was commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded out of the bride-houſe, and caſt into vtter dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and no man did once intreate for him. Looke into the 25. of <hi>Matthew</hi> and 28. verſe, and you ſhall there likewiſe ſee, that the ſeruant which had receiued but one talent, and without any employment to his maſters aduantage had hid it in the earth, had his ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent taken from him, and was caſt into vtter darkneſſe, and no man intreated for him. Nay, looke but into the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:16325:38"/> verſe going next before my text, and you ſhall heare the fiue fooliſh virgins crying: <hi>Lord, Lord, open vnto vs.</hi> And receiuing this vncomfortable anſwer from the mouth of comfort it ſelfe:<note place="margin">Ini <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>um Deus ſcit in examine, neſcit in amore. Greg. in Iob lib. <hi>11</hi> cap <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Neſcio vos, I know you not;</hi> that is, I haue reiected you, I haue reprobated you; and none, no not their late familiar friends and compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the other wiſe virgins, requeſted fauour for them.</p>
            <p>Againe, here vpon earth though no man intreate for an offender, yet oftentimes the freſh memory of his anceſtors good deeds, and the good demerits of his friends that be liuing, may moue the Iudge to pity and compaſſion: but for a man to truſt to this fauour in the day of iudgement, were to leane vpon a broken reed; for the men that do beſt fulfill the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, are tearmed in the 17. of Saint <hi>Luke</hi> and 10. verſe, <hi>Serui inutiles, Vnprofitable ſeruants.</hi> And then as the fiue wiſe virgins anſwered the fiue foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, <hi>(Mat. 25.9.)</hi> We cannot giue you of our oile, leaſt peraduenture there will not be enough for vs &amp; you: ſo the beſt men that be, cannot lend their friends any of their good workes; for if they do, without all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture they will leaue too few for themſelues.</p>
            <p>And thirdly, though neither of theſe two do come to paſſe, yet many times the ſubtiltie of the offender, and his cunning contriued ſpeech, do ouer-reach the wiſedome of the Iudge: but this hope ſhall faile a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in the day of iudgement. Our firſt mother <hi>Eue,</hi> ſo much as in her lay, ſhe did hide her ſin from God; and ſo did <hi>Cain</hi> the death of <hi>Abel:</hi> and haply ſaith S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambroſ. in Pſa. <hi>118.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>in affectu habemus abſcondere, non in effectu:</hi> we may with them affect the hiding of our ſins from God, but we neuer can effect it. In the 20. of S. <hi>Luke</hi>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:16325:38"/> and the 20. verſe, the Scribes and Phariſes come with cunning contriued ſpeeches vnto Chriſt, hoping to intrap him; but as cunning as they were, our Sauiour was too cunning for them: for in the 23. verſe, <hi>Quid tentatis hypocritae? Why tempt you me, ye hypocrites?</hi> And ſurely if craft and ſubtiltie could not ouertake our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour when he came in humilitie, much leſſe ſhall he be ouertaken thereby when he ſhall come in glory.</p>
            <p>And fourthly, though neither of theſe three doe happen in our earthly iudgements, yet we ſee by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience that witneſſes are oft kept backe, and by that meanes the priſoner is ſet free: but at Chriſt his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vnto iudgement, there is no ſuch aduantage to be expected. For, as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> well obſerues, in a mans owne houſe, and in a mans owne family,<note place="margin">Deuotiſ. medit. cap. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> he ſhal not faile of his accuſer, his witneſſe, and his iudge. <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſat conſcientia, teſtis eſt memoria, ratio index:</hi> his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience that will be his accuſer, his memory that will be his witneſſe, and his reaſon that will be his iudge to condemne him. And leaſt it ſhould be obiected that a mans memory may faile, and ſo conſequently the witneſſe, behold then a witneſſe whom nothing can cauſe to faile: <hi>Becauſe they haue done villany in Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, and committed adultery with their neighbours wiues, euen I ſee it, and I teſtifie it, ſaith the Lord.</hi> Ier. 29.23.</p>
            <p>And fiftly, though neither of theſe fall out, yet if a man be nobly borne, &amp; deſcend from honorable and princely parents, then none almoſt dare meddle with him, or once call his ſinnes in queſtion. But as <hi>Mordo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay</hi> in the fourth of <hi>Eſter</hi> and 15. verſe, ſaid vnto the Queene, when as the ſentence of death was paſt vpon all the people of the Iewes in the kingdomes of <hi>Aſſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus;</hi>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:16325:39"/> thinke not with thy ſelfe that thou ſhalt eſcape in the Kings houſe, more then all the Iewes: ſo at the day of iudgement, when all our ſins ſhall be layd open before God, men, and Angels, it is not our noble and honorable bloud, it is not a Kings houſe, nor a Kings linage that can exempt vs. But may not mony procure vs fauour with the Iudge, and be a meanes to ſtay the courſe of iuſtice? Indeed I confeſſe that mony may do much with earthly Iudges; it may turne iudgement into mercy, and mercy into iudgement: but it is not the multitude of gifts (ſaith <hi>Iob</hi> in his 36. chap. and 18. verſe) that can deliuer thee fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wrath of the Iudge of heauen.</p>
            <p>But ſay, none of all theſe do preuaile in our earthly iudgements, yet either by the conniuencie of the Iai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, or the weakneſſe of the priſon, a condemned man may eſcape: but after the ſentence is once pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in this laſt iudgement, both theſe comforts will faile a ſinner. For firſt the diuell, who is Iaylor, will be ſo vigilant, as no priſoner committed to his iayle ſhall haue leaue to depart. And for the ſecond, which is breaking of priſon, that is impoſſible for thoſe who are bound hand and foote, and ſo are ſinners bound after iudgement, <hi>Matth. 22.13. Take him and bind him hand and foote, and cast him into vtter darkneſſe.</hi> And yet ſuppoſe that they could vnlooſe themſelues, as ſome that are bound may do, yet is there no hope of euaſion: for in the 16. of <hi>Luke</hi> and 26. verſe, it is <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> ſpeech vnto the rich man in hell: <hi>Betweene you and vs there is a great gulfe, ſo that we cannot come vnto you, neither can you come vnto vs.</hi> So that hitherto you ſee this comming of Chriſt vnto iudgement to be ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:16325:39"/> But if we ſhall now a little farther conſider the rigor &amp; ſeueritie of the ſentence, which ſhall be thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered from the mouth of the Iudge againſt the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked; I make no queſtion but the terror thereof wil ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare much greater. The ſentence is ſet downe in the 25. of <hi>Mathew,</hi> and 41. verſe, <hi>Depart from me ye curſed into euerlaſting fire, which is prepared for the Diuell and his Angels.</hi> In which words,<note place="margin">Poena damni.</note> firſt the puniſhment of loſſe, as the Diuines terme it, contained in theſe words <hi>Depart from me,</hi> doth declare the ſeueritie of the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. For if one day in Gods courts be better then a thouſand elſewhere, as the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith in the 84. Pſalme and 10. verſe: then to be not onely a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeares, but for euer elſewhere, and not one day in the courts of God, it muſt needs be a grieuous and a great puniſhment. For a man to loſe his lands here in this world, what a vexation and griefe is it to many men? it doth oft times driue men vnto their wits end: how then thinke we will ſinners be affected and affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in mind, who when Chriſt Ieſus by his moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious bloud hath purchaſed for them no worſe land then the land of the liuing, the kingdome of heauen, they by their wilfull rebellion will be the occaſion of the loſſe of it? Were not the Iſraelites grieued thinke you, when from a ſorrowfull heart they told <hi>Moſes</hi> that he had brought them from a land which flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed with milke and honey, into a barren wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to deſtroy them with famine? And will it not be a greater torment to the wicked in the laſt day, when they ſhall heare and ſee themſelues baniſhed from heauen, and the preſence of God, in whoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, as the Pſalmiſt ſaith, Pſal. 16. and laſt verſe, there
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:16325:40"/> is fulneſſe of ioy, and at whoſe right hand there are pleaſures for euermore; and then ſent into a place where there is a famine of all good things, a famine of ioy, a famine of eaſe, a famine of the comfortable pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God? Surely if the Apoſtles for that litle time that Chriſt told them he was to be abſent from them, they were ſo ſorowfull and ſad, <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.21. that Chriſt himſelfe meaſureth their mourning by the mourning of a woman in her trauell. And if <hi>Peter,</hi> to whom Chriſt had ſaid,<note place="margin">Iohn 13.8.</note> 
               <hi>If I waſh thee not, thou ſhalt haue no part with me,</hi> was ſo loth to part with Chriſt, that he ſaid, <hi>Lord, not my feete onely, but my hands and my head alſo:</hi> in what caſe ſhall miſerable and accurſed ſinners be, who not for a time onely, but for all eternitie are ſhut out and baniſhed from the ſight of God?</p>
            <p>As then the rigor and ſeueritie of the Iudiciall ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence appeareth in the puniſhment of loſſe, ſo is it greatly amplified by the puniſhment of ſenſe;<note place="margin">Poena ſenſus.</note> for they are not only baniſhed by the Iudge from heauen, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from me;</hi> but they are ſent into a place of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, into hell fire. The Epicure, ſaith <hi>Tertullian,</hi> doth eſtimate all ſorrow and puniſhment after this maner: <hi>Modicus cruciatus eſt contemptibilis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul. aduerſ. Gentes. cap. <hi>45.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>magnus non eſt diu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnus:</hi> If the puniſhment be but ſmall, then a man of any ſpirit will contemne it; and if it be great, this is the comfort, that it cannot laſt long. But (ſaith he) the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picure deceiues himſelfe, becauſe the lawes of God do promiſe either an euerlaſting reward to the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, or a perpetuall puniſhment to the breakers. And therfore the ſentence runs not thus, <hi>Ite in ignem,</hi> Go into fire, though that had bin a great and a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous puniſhment; but to make it the more grieuous
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:16325:40"/> and the more terrible, they are commended <hi>in ignem aeternum,</hi> into euerlaſting fire. Grieuous were the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments that were inflicted vpon <hi>Adam</hi> for his ſin, (Gen. 3.) for firſt he was caſt out of Paradiſe, and then he was ſent into a place of thornes and thiſtles, there to eate his bread in the ſweat of his brow all the dayes of his life: but far more grieuous wil be the puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of <hi>Adams</hi> wicked children at the day of iudgement; for firſt they ſhall be depriued of heauen, a place more beautifull then Paradiſe, and then they ſhall be caſt into a burning lake, which is a farre worſe place then a place of thornes and thiſtles. And whereas <hi>Adam</hi> found this comfort in his puniſhment, that there was a <hi>donec in terram</hi> in it, that at laſt there wold be an end, the end of his life was the period of his puniſhment: yet the puniſhment of his wicked poſteritie ſhall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit no limitation of time, but they ſhall go (ſaith the Iudge) into euerlaſting fire, that is, they ſhall burne for euer and euer in that lake of fire. Indeed is were ſome comfort if they were to ſuffer this puniſhment no more thouſands of yeares then there be ſands on the ſea ſhore, or graſſe piles vpon the ground, or no more millions of ages then there are creatures in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, in earth, and in the ſea; for then were there ſome hope that at laſt there would be an end. But to be ſent <hi>in ignem aeternum,</hi> into euerlaſting fire, that is, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually to burne, and neuer to be burned vp, and after infinite millions of ages to be as farre from an end as at the firſt entrance into this torment, this is ſo ſeuere and rigorous a doome, as neither the tongues of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels or of men are able to expreſſe it.</p>
            <p>And as the rigor of the doome appeares, firſt by the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:16325:41"/> puniſhment of loſſe, in that they are commaunded out of Gods preſence, <hi>Depart from me;</hi> and ſecondly by the puniſhment of ſenſe, in that they are ſent, not onely into fire, but into euerlaſting fire. So to make it euery way complete, that nothing more might be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to it; vnto the former words of this ſentence, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me into euerlaſting fire,</hi> the Iudge doth adioyne theſe latter, <hi>which is prepared for the Diuell and his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.</hi> Men that are in miſery, they are commonly of this mind and nature, that they would not haue their friends and acquaintance come into the like miſery; and therefore the purple glutton (<hi>Luke</hi> 16.27.) being in hell, maketh this requeſt vnto <hi>Abraham: Father A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, ſend Lazarus I pray thee to my fathers houſe, that he may teſtifie vnto my fiue brethren, leaſt they alſo come into this place of torment.</hi> And as men are loth to haue their friends companions in their miſery; ſo are they as loth to haue thoſe their companions who wil helpe to augment and increaſe their miſeries: but the wicked, that their ſentence of condemnation might appeare the greater, they ſhal not only alwayes burne, but their companions in this fire ſhall be the Diuell and his Angels. When the Iewes ſate in iudgement vpon our Sauiour Chriſt, they reſolued vpon theſe three things againſt him: firſt, that he muſt be taken from among them; ſecondly, that he muſt die the ſhamefull and ignominious death of the croſſe; and thirdly, to do him the greater diſgrace, as they thought to vexe him the more; he muſt die in the companie of two theeues. And therefore hereafter, when Chriſt ſhall come in his glory to iudge the ſinnes both of Iewes and Gentiles, he will reſolue vpon three the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:16325:41"/> like for them, which they reſolued for him. For firſt, as they could not abide his preſence, and therefore they cryed <hi>tollite</hi> take him away: ſo he will not abide their preſence, but will ſay vnto them, <hi>Diſcedite a me Depart from me.</hi> And ſecondly, as they reſolued vpon no honorable death for him, but ſuch a death as was inflicted vpon vile and ignominious perſons: ſo the maner of dying which he allotteth vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ſuch, as belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth only vnto people that are curſed. And laſt of all, as they which did die with Chriſt were no better then theeues: ſo their friends in torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t are the fiends, and their companions in fire are the diuell and his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels. And therfore for the concluſion of this point, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member onely that ſhort, but ſweete caueat which <hi>S. Austin</hi> giueth, writing vpon the 80. Pſalme, <hi>Si non ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes mitti quó, vide cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quo,</hi> If thou art not afraid to burn for thy ſinnes in hell, yet be afraid to burne with ſuch helliſh companions as are the diuell and his Angels. And thus haue you ſeene the terror of Chriſt his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vnto iudgement, as by other other circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſo eſpecially by the rigor &amp; ſeuerity of the Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſentence; which firſt depriueth them of heauen, <hi>Depart from me:</hi> and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> adiugeth them to hell, Go in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to fire. Thirdly, there to burne not for a time but for euer, into euerlaſting fire; and that with no better co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions then the diuell and his Angels. I come now to the third point, and this is:</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the time of this terrible coming vnto iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is vncertaine. For we know not, ſaith my text, either day or houre when it will be.</p>
            <p>In the third verſe of the chapter going before, the 24. of <hi>Mathew,</hi> the diſciples of our Sauiour being
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:16325:42"/> deſirous to be reſolued of a double doubt, firſt at what time the temple of Ieruſalem ſhold be deſtroyed, and ſecondly, when his laſt coming vnto iudgment ſhould be; our Sauiour Chriſt for their better inſtruction tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them that there ſhall be warres, and rumours of warres, that nation ſhall riſe againſt nation, and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome againſt kingdome, that there ſhall be peſtilence, and famine, &amp; earthquakes in diuers places. All which ſignes with many other in that chapter, though ſome haue reſtrained to the firſt queſtion of the deſtruction of Ieruſalem: yet according to the iudgement of the moſt interpreters, they containe a mixt anſwer vnto both, and are ſignes not only of the particular deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but alſo of the finall diſſolution of the whole world in the day of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And grant this, yet no other collectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can fitly be gathered hence, but that which Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> long ſince obſerued, <hi>Modum patefecit, tempus celare voluit:</hi> He concealeth the time, and expreſſeth onely the manner of his coming. And therefore for any man to thinke himſelfe ſufficiently inſtructed of the time of Chriſt his coming by reaſon of thoſe prognoſticke ſignes which our Sauiour hath ſet downe, it is a groſſe and a fooliſh impiety. Yea ſaith Saint <hi>Austin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. 7 8.</note> to take a computation of times, that therby we may know when the end of the world and Chriſt his coming ſhall be; <hi>Nihil videtur aliud, quàm ſcire velle, quod Christus ait ſcire neminem poſſe:</hi> It is nothing elſe, but to be deſirous to know that, which our Sauiour Chriſt hath ſaid no man can know. <hi>For of that day and houre knoweth no man,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.36. <hi>no not the Angels of heauen, but my Father onely.</hi> Nay, in the 13. of Saint <hi>Marke,</hi> and 32. verſe, he excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:16325:42"/> againſt himſelf, to leue the high knowledge ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to his Father; <hi>Of that day and houre knoweth no man, no not the Angels which are in heauen, neither the Sonne himſelfe,</hi> (as he is man only) <hi>ſaue the Father.</hi> And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that the world might be the better reſolued in this point, in the vncertainty of his coming vnto iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; beſides thoſe many watchwords of his to the world: It is not for you to know the times and ſeaſons which the father hath put in his owne power.<note place="margin">Math. 24.42. Math. 25.13. Mark. 13.33.</note> You know not what houre your maiſter will come. You know not the day nor the houre when the Sonne of man will come. Yee know not when the time is, and the like: He hath in the Goſpell compared his coming vnto three things, which come moſt ſodainly and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are aware: and theſe are; a ſnare, a thiefe, and the floud of <hi>Noah.</hi> In the 21. of <hi>Luke,</hi> and 34. verſe, he reſembleth the day of his coming vnto iudgement to a ſnare: <hi>Take heed vnto your ſelues leaſt at any time your hearts be ouercome with ſurfetting, and drunkenneſſe, and the cares of this life, and leaſt that day come on you at vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares; for as a ſnare ſhall it come on all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that dwell on the face of the whole earth.</hi> A ſnare you know enta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gleth on the ſodaine, and the birds and wilde beaſts whilſt f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>areleſſe of danger they are intentiue to their foode, they ſodainly fall into it. And ſo it is with man, ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> he conſidereth not his end, Eccleſ. 9.12. But as the fiſhes which are taken in a net, and as the birds which are caught in a ſnare; ſo are the children of men ſnared in the euill, when it falleth ſodain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon them. Men may feaſt it merrily with <hi>Iobs</hi> children,<note place="margin">Iob. 1.19. Dan. 5.3</note> and be frolick with their companions amidſt their cups, with <hi>Balthaſſar;</hi> and as it is in the 21. of <hi>Iob,</hi>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:16325:43"/> they may call for <hi>the Tabret and the Harpe, and reioyce in the ſound of Organs: but on the ſodaine euen before they be aware,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. Epiſt. <hi>80.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>they go downe into the graue,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iob,</hi> that is, they fal into the ſnare of death, and ſo conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into the ſnare of iudgement. For, <hi>Qualis in die iſto quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> moritur, talis in die illo iudicabitur:</hi> as the day of mans death leaues him, ſo the day of Gods laſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall finde him. And as Chriſt for the ſodaineſſe &amp; vncertainty of his coming, compareth it to a ſnare; ſo he compareth it likewiſe to the coming of a theefe. <hi>Math.</hi> 24.43. <hi>If the good man of the houſe did know at what houre the theefe would come, he would ſurely watch, and not ſuffer his houſe to be digged through.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be ye alſo ready: for in the houre ye think not, wil the ſon of man come. The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> in his ſecond Epiſtle 3.10. makes the ſame reſemblance. <hi>The day of the Lord will come euen as a theefe in the night, in the which the heauens ſhall paſſe away with a noyſe, and the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements ſhall melt with heat, and the earth with the works that are therein ſhall be burnt vp.</hi> And Saint <hi>Paule</hi> (1. Theſſ. 5.2.) handling the ſame argument, hath the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſame. <hi>The day of the Lord ſhall come as a theefe in the night, and when men ſhall ſay peace and ſafety, then ſhall come vpon them ſodaine destruction, as the trauell vpon a woman with child, and they ſhall not eſcape.</hi> And as the day of Chriſt his comming is compared for the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaintie thereof vnto a ſnare and a theefe: ſo for the ſame cauſe it is compared by him to the floud of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah. Math.</hi> 24.36. <hi>As the dayes of Noah were, ſo likewiſe</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>ſhal the comming of the Sonne of man be: For as in the dayes before the floud, they did eate &amp; drink, mary, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> giue in mariage, vnto the day that Noah en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:16325:43"/> into the Ark, and knew nothing til the floud came and tooke them all away: ſo ſhall alſo the comming of the ſonne of man be.</hi> And therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat anſwer which our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our gaue to the Phariſes queſtion, <hi>Luk.</hi> 17. and 20. v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. may well be the concluſion of this point. The king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God cometh not with obſeruation, that is (ſaith the Gloſſe) it cometh not with the obſeruation of the time: as if he had ſaid; haply ſome Aſtronomer or other is ſo cunning as to tell you when the cloudes will drop: but at what time the Sonne of man ſhall come to iudgement in the cloudes, no Aſtronomer is ſo cunning as to tell you that; for of that day &amp; houre knoweth no man, no not the Angels in heauen, nor the Sonne himſelfe, but the Father onely. Well then (beloued) theſe three points being thus cleared; Firſt that their will be a comming of the Sonne of man to iudgement. Secondly that this his comming vnto iudgement will be fearfull, and terrible. And thirdly that the time of this his comming is vncertaine, we know not when: what remaineth now but the vſe which we are to make of all theſe? and that is a vigilant and carefull preparation of our ſelues againſt his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, preſcribed in the firſt words: <hi>Vigilate igitur: Watch therefore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt of <hi>Ieremy,</hi> the Prophet at the firſt ſaw no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a rod, but after (ſaith the text) he beheld ſeething pot. And ſo the wicked and vngodly people, haply they may ſee and feele in this world nothing but rods, light and ſlight puniſhments: but the time will come when <hi>Salomons</hi> rods ſhall be turned into <hi>Rehoboams</hi> Scorpions, and the Prophet <hi>Ieremies</hi> rod will proue a ſeething pot. For as fleſh is p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> into a ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:16325:44" rendition="simple:additions"/> pot: ſo the bodies and ſoules of men, in regard of their ſinnes committed in the fleſh, ſhall be caſt into the ſeething and boyling lake of hell. At which time they ſhall haue nothing to comfort them, either aboue them or beneath them, on the right hand or on the left, within them or without them. Aboue them ſhall be the angry Iudge, for their wickedneſſe condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them; beneath them ſhal be hel open, and the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace boyling to receiue them: on their right hand ſhal be their ſinnes accuſing them, on their left hand the diuels ready to execute Gods eternall ſentence on them; within them ſhall be their conſcience gnaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, without them the damned ſoules wailing, and round about them the whole world burning. Good Lord, good Lord, ſaith a deuout father, what will a wretched ſinner do enuironed with all theſe miſeries? how will his heart ſuſtaine theſe anguiſhes? what way will he take? to go backe (ſaith he) it is impoſſible, and to go forward, it is intollerable. And ſurely all this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing true, and drawne by neceſſary conſequent from the word of God, me thinkes now there ſhould need no watchword at all, and our Sauiour Chriſt his <hi>vigilate igitur</hi> in this place may ſeeme ſuperfluous. The heathen man did both ſay and beleeue,<note place="margin">Tul. de nat. deor. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> that whoſoeuer remembreth that God will reward the godly and puniſh the vngodly, he cannot but be god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And if this be not true in vs that are Chriſtians, then, as <hi>Clymacus</hi> well obſerues, <hi>Plus timebimus canem, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Creatore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> we ſhal ſhew our ſelues to be more afraid of our dog, then we are of our God. If a theefe do aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault our houſe in the night, and our dogge which is within do but barke, we need no further <hi>vigilate,</hi> we
<pb facs="tcp:16325:44"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> warning: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſe, and we will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Our Sauiour Chriſt then haui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> many times, that he will on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that his comming will be (as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and terrible, and that the time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> is moſt vncertaine, we know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> now any further <hi>vigilate,</hi> any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> prepare our ſelues againſt this comming <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued) a very cleare caſe, that the barking of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> wil preuaile more with vs for the ſauing of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> then the voice of our God for the ſauing of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> When <hi>Ioſeph</hi> had forewarned <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of Aegypt of that great famine which was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> vpon the land, there was no further <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> be vigilant. And if they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo care<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> momentary death of body; ough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to be vigilant how to preuent the e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of ſoule and body? Well then, how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> our ſelues that our true vigilancie ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> thus, ſaith Saint <hi>Bernard: Audiſti edictu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>dictum:</hi> Haſt thou heard of the fearefull <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> which God hath determined to powre vp <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> beware then of ſinne which will be the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> puniſhment. But is this all? no, the watc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> well ſet: for the ſame ſpirit which ſaith (Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Flie from euill;</hi> immediatly addeth, <hi>and do</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 14. of <hi>Luke</hi> and 31. verſe: <hi>What King</hi> (ſaith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>going to make warre againſt another King, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> downe firſt, and taketh counſell, whether he be ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ten thouſands to meete him which commeth ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſt him with twentie thouſands? or elſe while he is yet a grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:16325:45"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>olicie betw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rre better policie betw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſinnes grieue God more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> can vexe his neighbor king <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ter diſproportion between <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſtrength of God, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of ten thouſands, and an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ands. Firſt then let vs ſeriouſly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> counſell, whether we may boldly ſay with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 3. verſe 18. <hi>Behold now, if I prepare me vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, I know that I ſhall be iuſtified.</hi> And if we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> this perſwaſion in regard of our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> contempt of Gods commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> muſt be our ſecond courſe, euen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> off, that is, while his grace by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the Goſpell is offered vnto vs: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and vnfained repentance as an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> him, deſiring him that he would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om his throne of iuſtice, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> his throne of mercy. That ſo in that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> full day of his comming, we may not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> euerlaſting horror of our ſoules that fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Go ye curſed into euerlaſting fire which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> diuel and his angels;</hi> but to the endleſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> our ſoules, that other comfortable ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e ye bleſſed of my Father, inherite the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dome prepared for you from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the beginning of the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:16325:45"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
